<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>disentangle</title>
		<description>Disentangle Things</description>
		<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com</link>
		
			<item>
				<title>sanitize-mendeley-references-in-r-markdown-reporting</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;A key challenge for Reproducible Research Reports in Rmarkdown remains adequate scholarly citation management; the machinery of scholarly citations and references.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;knitcitations&lt;/code&gt; R package does a great job of working with bibtex bibliography files, however the bibtex manager that I use is Mendeley and it has implemented some rules on the way it handles special characters that forces the bibtex references into a state with some 'escaped' elements that breaks their presentation via &lt;code&gt;knitcitations&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a post from my open notebook that shows the workaround I am using for sanitizing the Mendeley escaped underscores in URLS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is considerable public health impact from the effects on mental of drought &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot;&gt;(&lt;span&gt;Sarathi Biswas&lt;/span&gt; 2012)&lt;/span&gt;. It is proposed that the best method to disentangle the multifactorial nature of this causal mechanism is the ‘five-capitals’ framework, indeed this method may even enable understanding the human carrying capacity of ecosystems &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot;&gt;(McMichael &amp;amp; Butler 2002)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;h1&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;McMichael, A.J. &amp;amp; Butler, C.D. (2002). Global health trends: Evidence for and against sustainable progress. &lt;em&gt;International Union for the Scientific Study of Population Committee on Emerging Health Threats&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.demogr.mpg.de/papers/workshops/020619{\_}paper25.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.demogr.mpg.de/papers/workshops/020619{\_}paper25.pdf&lt;/a&gt; [21 Sep. 2003]&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Sarathi Biswas&lt;/span&gt;, P. (2012). Alcohol, drought lead to farmer’s suicide. &lt;em&gt;Daily News and Analysis&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dnaindia.com/pune/report{\_}alcohol-drought-lead-to-farmers-suicide{\_}1688976&quot;&gt;http://www.dnaindia.com/pune/report{\_}alcohol-drought-lead-to-farmers-suicide{\_}1688976&lt;/a&gt; [17 May 2012]&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;See those pesky curly braces &lt;code&gt;{&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;}&lt;/code&gt; around the underscores?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The fix&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fix I am using is to sanitize each record where this is an issue as I build my document, so the mendeley version stays as-is, while the R version has been sanitized by removing the escape characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# read mendeley bibtex file
bib &amp;lt;- read.bibtex(&quot;~/references/library.bib&quot;)
# ad hoc fix
for(bibkey in c(&quot;SarathiBiswas2012&quot;,
  &quot;Mcmichael2002a&quot;  
)){
  bib[ [ bibkey ] ]$url &amp;lt;- gsub(&quot;\\{\\\\_\\}&quot;,&quot;_&quot;, bib[ [ bibkey ] ]$url)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McMichael, A.J. &amp;amp; Butler, C.D. (2002). Global health trends: Evidence for and against sustainable progress. &lt;em&gt;International Union for the Scientific Study of Population Committee on Emerging Health Threats&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.demogr.mpg.de/papers/workshops/020619_paper25.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.demogr.mpg.de/papers/workshops/020619_paper25.pdf&lt;/a&gt; [21 Sep. 2003]&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Sarathi Biswas&lt;/span&gt;, P. (2012). Alcohol, drought lead to farmer’s suicide. &lt;em&gt;Daily News and Analysis&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dnaindia.com/pune/report_alcohol-drought-lead-to-farmers-suicide_1688976&quot;&gt;http://www.dnaindia.com/pune/report_alcohol-drought-lead-to-farmers-suicide_1688976&lt;/a&gt; [17 May 2012]&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<published>2015-10-24 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/10/sanitize-mendeley-references-in-r-markdown-reporting/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Keeping an electronic lab notebook for computational statistics projects</title>
				<description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In my previous post on this topic &lt;a href=&quot;http://ivanhanigan.github.io/2015/10/how-to-effectively-implement-electronic-lab-notebooks-in-epidemiology/&quot;&gt;http://ivanhanigan.github.io/2015/10/how-to-effectively-implement-electronic-lab-notebooks-in-epidemiology/&lt;/a&gt; I summarised some recommendations for electronic lab notebooks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've collated from a variety of sources for managing computational statistics projects in a reproducible research Pipelines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One thing I found while reading the literature around this topic is that the concepts are difficult to really grasp until I see them being used&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The example worklog from Scott Long was a good insight into his method, that I really got more out of the figure below than from descriptions of the concept&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;screen shot taken from Long, S. (2012). Principles of Workflow in Data Analysis. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiana.edu/~wim/docs/2012-long-slides.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.indiana.edu/~wim/docs/2012-long-slides.pdf&lt;/a&gt; (accessed 2015-10-23).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/worklog-long.png&quot; alt=&quot;/images/worklog-long.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I added a red box around an important aspect of this example, the communication of gory details, that are often difficult to track if not using a notebook to log our work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ARGH! indeed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Replication from Noble's description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That looks good, but I also really liked the description in Noble's paper where scripts that do computations are linked to log entries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was something that I felt I wanted to see in action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Without an example online, I had to have a go at creating one from the instructions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also had to make some modifications to the method because I want to have this set up work in a multidisciplinary team with some users on windows and others on linux, sharing the project on a network folder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;My paraphrasing of Noble's description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Worklog: this is the main file, like a 'lab notebook' for the analyst to track their work.  This  document resides in the root of the project directory and records your progress in detail. Entries in the notebook should be dated, and they should be relatively verbose, with links or embedded images or tables displaying the results of the experiments that you performed. In addition to describing precisely what you did, the notebook should record your observations, conclusions, and ideas for future work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For group work, this can also contain a 'working' folder for each person to store their messy day-to-day files that we don't want to clutter up the main folder (eg 'working_ivan')&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Conventions I used for writing the worklog entries are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Names follow this structure [**] [date in ISO 8601 YYYY-MM-DD] [meeting/notes/results] [with/from UserName] [Re: topic shortname]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;'meetings' are for both agenda preparation and also notes of discussion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;'notes' are such things as emailed information or ad hoc Discovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;'results' are entries related to a section of the 'results' folder. That is, this kind of entry is in parallel to the results entry (see below), however the log contains a prose description of the experiment, whereas the results folder contains scripts etc of all the gory details.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Tests&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I use Emacs on linux for most of my work but I need to share with windows users so tested out keeping the log in a MS word doc.  This got corrupted quickly I think because I edited in Libre office.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I decided to try and just use a plain text format&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;text files created in Ubuntu are so difficult to understand (read) when opened in Windows' Notepad. No matter how many lines have been used, all the lines appear in the same one line.
To set the buffer coding to DOS style issue:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;M-x set-buffer-file-coding-system utf-8-dos&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;a couple of examples&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As this is a plain text document opening it in emacs will not automatically render it in the Orgmode fashion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To achieve this the command is &lt;code&gt;M-x org-mode&lt;/code&gt; and the file looks like below&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/worklog-ivan1.png&quot; alt=&quot;/images/worklog-ivan1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From here I can keep adding new entries at the bottom, and have a section for URGENT ACTION a the top&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Orgmode can expand the entries by moving to that line and hitting TAB, or use the command &lt;code&gt;C-u C-u C-u TAB&lt;/code&gt; to expand all branches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/worklog-ivan2.png&quot; alt=&quot;/images/worklog-ivan2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;the 'Experiment Results' level is about work you might do on a single day, or over a week or two&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each results subfolder would have workflow scripts that does the work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At this level each 'experiment' is written up in chronological order&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is recommended to store every command used while performing the experiment preferably as an executable script that carries out the entire experiment automatically&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you should end up with a file that is parallel to the worklog entry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The worklog contains a prose description of the experiment, whereas the driver script contains all the gory details&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this is the level I usually think of the distribution side of things&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You may want to pack up the results from one of these folders and email it to the collaborators, or decide on the one set of tables and figures to write into the manuscript for submission to a journal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If this is accepted for publication, this is the one combined package of 'analytical data and code' that I would consider putting up online as supporting information for the paper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Example&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I followed Noble's advice to create a driver script to set up the folder structure:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is in my Github R package &lt;code&gt;disentangle&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; dir.create(&quot;exposures_blending&quot;)
&amp;gt; setwd(&quot;exposures_blending&quot;)
&amp;gt; disentangle::AdminTemplate()
[1] TRUE
&amp;gt; dir.create(&quot;results&quot;)
&amp;gt; setwd(&quot;results&quot;)
&amp;gt; makeProject::makeProject(&quot;2015-10-23-preliminary-modelling&quot;)
Creating Directories ...
Creating Code Files ...
Complete ...
&amp;gt; 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This populates the folders as shown below&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/worklog-ivan3.png&quot; alt=&quot;/images/worklog-ivan3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I feel pretty happy with this as a replication of Noble's method&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My colleagues can look at my work and see a high level log that links to the gory details of day to day life in the trenches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The only downside I can see at the moment is that my colleagues on windows will see a text file that is pretty dense, and will not be as easy to navigate as a word document (or emacs org file)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perhaps notepad++ can be used instead.  On my windows machine I did a quick experiment with NPP and found that under the Language menu &gt; Define your language there is a method to define code folding with ** as the opening.  Just need to define a closing tag.  I experimented with '---' which might be good, but ultimately I don't think my colleagues are going to want to do this on their machines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<published>2015-10-23 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/10/keeping-an-electronic-lab-notebook-for-computational-statistics-projects/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Reproducible research pipelines improve description of method steps</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Adequately documenting the methods and results of data analysis helps
safeguard against errors of execution and
interpretation. It is proposed that
reproducible research pipelines address the problem of
adequate documentation of data analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because they make it easy to
check the methods. Assumptions are easy to challenge and results
verified in new analyses. Reproducible research pipelines extend
traditional research.  They do this by encoding the steps in a
computer ‘scripting’ language and distributing the data and code with
publications.  Traditional research moves through the steps of
hypothesis and design, measured data, analytic data, computational
results (for figures, tables and numerical results), and reports (text
and formatted manuscript).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Fundamental components of a reproducible research pipeline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic components of a pipeline are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Management Plan and Data Inventory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Method steps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reports&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distribution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Method Steps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The method step is the key atomic unit of a scientific pipeline.  It consists of inputs, outputs and a rationale for why the step is taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple way to keep track of the steps, inputs and outputs is shown in the Table below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(stringr)
steps &amp;lt;- read.csv(textConnection('
CLUSTER ,  STEP  , INPUTS                   , OUTPUTS                   
A  ,  Step1      , &quot;Input 1, Input 2&quot;       , &quot;Output 1&quot;                 
A  ,  Step2      ,  Input 3                  , Output 2                   
B  ,  Step3      , &quot;Output 1, Output 2&quot;      , Output 3                  
'), stringsAsFactors = F, strip.white = T)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The steps and data listed in the Table above can be visualised.
To achieve this an R function was written as part of this PhD project and is distributed in my own R package available on Github &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ivanhanigan/disentangle&quot;&gt;https://github.com/ivanhanigan/disentangle&lt;/a&gt;.
This is the &lt;code&gt;newnode&lt;/code&gt; function.  The function returns a string of text
written in the &lt;code&gt;dot&lt;/code&gt; language which can be rendered in R using the
&lt;code&gt;DiagrammeR&lt;/code&gt; package, or the standalone &lt;code&gt;graphviz&lt;/code&gt; package.   This creates the graph of this pipeline shown in Figure below.  Note that a new field was added for Descriptions as these are highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(disentangle); library(stringr)
nodes &amp;lt;- newnode(indat = steps,   names_col = &quot;STEP&quot;, in_col = &quot;INPUTS&quot;,
  out_col = &quot;OUTPUTS&quot;, 
  nchar_to_snip = 40)
sink(&quot;fig-basic.dot&quot;);
cat(nodes);
sink()
# or DiagrammeR::grViz(nodes)
system(&quot;dot -Tpdf fig-basic.dot -o fig-basic.pdf&quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fig-basic.png&quot; alt=&quot;/images/fig-basic.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2015-10-18 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/10/reproducible-research-pipelines-improve-description-of-method-steps/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>How To Effectively Implement Electronic Lab Notebooks In Epidemiology</title>
				<description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is often stated in the literature that an electronic lab notebook is a core component of reproducible research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For example the following is from Buck, S. (2015). Solving reproducibility. Science, 348(6242), 1403–1403. &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.aac8041&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.aac8041&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;one of the most effective ways to promote high-quality science 
is to create free open-source tools that give scientists
easier and cheaper ways to incorporate transparency
into their daily workflow: from open lab notebooks, to
software that tracks every version of a data set, to dynamic 
document generation.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But I have struggled to operationalise the lab notebook in the epidemiology projects I work in&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Here are some notes based on my recent readings and attempts with a new team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Modularised lab notebooks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There seem to be a small number of components to a lab notebook that can be defined as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data management plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workplan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Worklog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workflow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distribution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing I think is important is to have levels of organisation in a hierarchy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Macro level: The 'Research Programme' level is about the entire breadth of the projects in the group.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Management Plan: including managing the computers and a Data Inventory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Personal Workplan and Worklog&lt;/em&gt;: this is an overview of things I do, plan to do or learn along the way (this is for the high level things like planning professional development, or a holiday)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is operationalised in the blog you are reading right now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meso level: the 'Research Project' level is about a single study, or a small group of studies based around a core dataset or Concept

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is the level that you might write up a manuscript for a journal, or report to a client&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Project workplan&lt;/em&gt;: at this level there may be high level information about the study design, hypotheses, resources and admin for managing relationships with a variety of collaborators&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Worklog&lt;/em&gt;: WS Noble &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000424&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000424&lt;/a&gt; recommends that this be the main lab notebook for the analysts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He says 'This is a document that resides in the root of the results directory and that records your progress in detail. Entries in the notebook should be dated, and they should be relatively verbose, with links or embedded images or tables displaying the results of the experiments that you performed. In addition to de- scribing precisely what you did, the notebook should record your observations, conclusions, and ideas for future work'&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Micro level: the 'Experiment Results' level is about work you might do on a single day, or over a week

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Workflow&lt;/em&gt; scripts: At this level each 'experiment' is written up in chronological order, as entries to the Worklog at the meso level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Noble recommends 'create either a README file, in which I store every command line that I used while performing the experi- ment, or a driver script (I usually call this runall) that carries out the entire experiment automatically'...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and 'you should end up with a file that is parallel to the lab notebook entry. The lab notebook contains a prose description of the exper- iment, whereas the driver script contains all the gory details.'&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this is the level I usually think of managing the distribution side of things.  I will want to pack up the results and email to my collaborators, or decide on the one set of tables and figures to write into the manuscript for submission to a journal.  If this is accepted for publication, this is the one combined package of 'analytical data and code' that I would consider putting up online (to github) as supporting information for the paper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<published>2015-10-17 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/10/how-to-effectively-implement-electronic-lab-notebooks-in-epidemiology/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>GIS Issues when R is Used for Transforming Coordinate Systems</title>
				<description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have been using RGDAL to transform and write out spatial data in GDA94&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is a problem to know what I need to do to create the right prj file for ArcGIS to read without complaining&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have an example of code below, that I used on a dataset I knew was in GDA94 when I read it in.  I want to do this mostly for when I have to convert from one to another, but I have done the manual hack a couple of times now and thought I better just check with an expert.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;R Code:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;infile &amp;lt;- &quot;ap_map&quot;
outfile &amp;lt;- gsub(&quot;map&quot;, &quot;map_GDA94.shp&quot;, infile)
outfile
setwd(indir)
shp &amp;lt;- readOGR(&quot;.&quot;, infile)
setwd(projdir)
plot(shp, add = T)
#str(shp)
shp@proj4string@projargs
#[1] &quot;+proj=longlat +ellps=GRS80 +no_defs&quot;
# confirm this is GDA94
epsg &amp;lt;- make_EPSG()
str(epsg)
epsg[grep(4283, epsg$code),]
#     code    note                                                       prj4
# 212 4283 # GDA94   +proj=longlat +ellps=GRS80 +towgs84=0,0,0,0,0,0,0 +no_defs
# Arcmap sees this as GRS 1980(IUGG, 1980) which I think is the same thing
# to be on the safe side I will force it to refer to GDA94
shp2 &amp;lt;- spTransform(shp, CRS(&quot;+init=epsg:4283&quot;))
shp2@proj4string@projargs
#now write
setwd(outdir)
dir()
writeOGR(shp2,  outfile, gsub(&quot;.shp&quot;, &quot;&quot;, outfile), driver = &quot;ESRI Shapefile&quot;)
setwd(projdir)
# Checking this shows it did not write the correct prj file, but I believe that this is because the GDA94 definition is not different to the WGS80 params.
# one other option is to manually replace that prj file with the correct text found at http://spatialreference.org/ref/epsg/4283/
# SO I did this to avoid any future confusions
# OLD GEOGCS[&quot;GRS 1980(IUGG, 1980)&quot;,DATUM[&quot;D_unknown&quot;,SPHEROID[&quot;GRS80&quot;,6378137,298.257222101]],PRIMEM[&quot;Greenwich&quot;,0],UNIT[&quot;Degree&quot;,0.017453292519943295]]
# NEW GEOGCS[&quot;GDA94&quot;,DATUM[&quot;D_GDA_1994&quot;,SPHEROID[&quot;GRS_1980&quot;,6378137,298.257222101]],PRIMEM[&quot;Greenwich&quot;,0],UNIT[&quot;Degree&quot;,0.017453292519943295]]
# checked with ArcMap and they align ok
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;I asked on of my colleagues and here is his reply&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I usually use the sp and maptools library, rather than the readOGR and writeOGR functions.  Generally my workflow, as an example of projecting a GDA94 zone 55 file to WGS84, would be something like:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;R Code:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;shp &amp;lt;- readShapePoly(&quot;myfile.shp&quot;)
proj4string(shp) &amp;lt;- &quot;+proj=utm +zone=55 +south +ellps=GRS80 +towgs84=0,0,0,0,0,0,0 +units=m +no_defs&quot;
shp2 &amp;lt;- spTransform(shp, CRS(&quot;+proj=longlat +ellps=WGS84 +datum=WGS84 +no_defs &quot;))
writePolyShape(shp2,&quot;myfile_p.shp&quot;,proj4string=CRS(&quot;+proj=longlat +ellps=WGS84 +datum=WGS84 +no_defs &quot;))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've never &lt;em&gt;noticed&lt;/em&gt; any problems doing this, the projection file is generated and I've never noticed any alignment problems in ArcMap.  It's true that I recall ArcMap sometimes displays an incorrect plaintext projection description, but things seem to be in the right place.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also, I don't really ever rely on EPSG numbers in R - I just grab the proj4 strings and try to use them directly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;TODO, see if PostGIS handles this OK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wonder if my FOSS GIS stack should still pass things through PostGIS as I suspect it does these things better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I might check the output if I run it through the DB use st_transform and then extract to shapefile.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<published>2015-10-16 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/10/gis-issues-when-r-used-transforming-coordinate-systems/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A Set Of Guidelines For Exploratory Data Analysis And Cleaning</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The New York Times ran a piece on August 17, 2014: “For Big-Data Scientists, ‘Janitor Work’ Is Key Hurdle to Insights” [1].  The article bemoaned the need for too much of what data scientists call “data wrangling”, “data munging” and “data janitor work”.  In essence this means data quality control processes.
A key task of my role as data manager/analyst is to perform Exploratory Data Analysis (EDA) to review data deposited for consistency, quality and its compliance with standards to ensure that reusability of data published in the portal is maximised.   To do this, I use relevant data formatting standards (for example the International Standards from ISO), undertake thorough taxonomic reviews of each dataset and have well documented procedures for dealing with miscellaneous errors such as data inconsistencies, duplicate variable names and reformatting numeric or character strings. I sometimes make changes to the data and give no further thoughts to it, but at  other times I need to make recommendations to the data provider and ask for their decisions/approvals on what to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have put down this set of guidelines for my procedures to create standardised data structures, based on things that have been recommended in the literature [2-6] to make data as re-usable as possible. Here is a list of standard amendments undertaken during my EDA process:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;identify any out-of-range values (based on the specified units), or questionable data in general;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rename all files and variables using lower_case_with_underscores naming convention;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tabulate frequencies and variable distributions, note any outliers for review;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;identify any opportunities to make wide data longer, or many files that can be merged;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have multiple linked tables, each table should include a column that allows those tables to be linked unambiguously (such as the site_ID variables); check that linking variables that link two or more data tables are identical in each table&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;check that values in linked files marry up to values in other files (eg a site code in one file that is missing from the spatial data file);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;write as CSV with quote encapsulated strings (for archival purposes);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;code missing data as NA, or identify if these were actually censored;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;coerce dates to ISO 8601 to be in the the YYYY-MM-DD format, or MMM-YYYY;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cast nominal variables that use integer codes as character;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;check that all value labels in enumerated lists are described (ie codes for “1” = “low”, “2” = “mid” and “3” = “high”);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;attempt to identify and split any combined variables (like season AND year like “winter-97” or species and comments ie “Banksia Dead”);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;review any species lists against current scientific name conventions, recommend any modifications;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rename any non-conformant species lists (for instance including comments such as Alive/Dead) to “fauna_descriptor” or “flora_descriptor”;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;identify any characters in numeric or date variables and replace with NA, (add to a comments variable if possible);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;identify any values that Excel may try to convert to date type (for eg. site code “1-5” will appear as 5-Jan and should be rewritten as “site_1-5”);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use a GIS to confirm spatial coordinates and add geographical coordinates in decimal degrees (GDA94) if only supplied in metres UTM or AMG (always request the datum and the zone);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;check what the coordinates refer to (e.g. approximate location of SW corner of 1ha plot).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rename files to be consistent with all data in the LTERN Data Portal.  Our standardised names have been created using controlled vocabularies.  Packages and files are designated tracking numbers – this is denoted by a plot network code and a unique “Package” number ascribed to each data package.  Each data package contains one or more data table which is the smallest trackable unit (denoted by a unique “Table” number).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;while we prefer deposit of plain text CSV files, if we receive Excel spreadsheets we check for hidden rows or columns that might not be intended for publication (and  may have been deposited as an oversight).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is always best to open Excel workbooks and use the in-built export function to save as CSV files for further re-use.  While R packages and other tools exist to programmatically extract the data from Excel, few tools that interoperate with Excel actually get the all the bug/feature cases right.  It has been noted that
&quot;because working with data that has passed through Excel is hard to get right, data that has passed through Excel is often wrong.&quot; [7]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;References:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lohr, S. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/08/18/technology/for-big-data-scientists-hurdle-to-insights-is-janitor-work.html?_r=0&quot;&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/08/18/technology/for-big-data-scientists-hurdle-to-insights-is-janitor-work.html?_r=0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;White, E., Baldridge, E., Brym, Z., Locey, K., McGlinn, D., &amp;amp; Supp, S. (2013). Nine simple ways to make it easier to (re)use your data. Ideas in Ecology and Evolution, 6(2), 1–10. &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.4033/iee.2013.6b.6.f&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.4033/iee.2013.6b.6.f&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wickham, H. (Under Review). Tidy data. Journal of Statistical Software, VV(Ii).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leek, J. 2014. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jtleek/datasharing&quot;&gt;https://github.com/jtleek/datasharing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Borer, E., Seabloom, E., Jones, M., and Schildhauer, M. 2009. Some Simple Guidelines for Effective Data Management. Bulletin of the Ecological Society of America 90:205–214. &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1890/0012-9623-90.2.205&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1890/0012-9623-90.2.205&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Campbell, J. L., Rustad, L. E., Porter, J. H., Taylor, J. R., Dereszynski, E. W., Shanley, J. B., Gries, C., Henshaw, D. L., Martin, M. E., Sheldon, W. M., and Boose, E. R. 2013. Quantity is Nothing
without Quality: Automated QA/QC for Streaming Environmental Sensor Data. BioScience, 63,
574-585. &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1525/bio.2013.63.7.10&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1525/bio.2013.63.7.10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mount, J. 2014. Excel spreadsheets are hard to get right. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.win-vector.com/blog/2014/11/excel-spreadsheets-are-hard-to-get-right/&quot;&gt;http://www.win-vector.com/blog/2014/11/excel-spreadsheets-are-hard-to-get-right/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</description>
				<published>2015-10-14 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/10/a-set-of-guidelines-for-exploratory-data-analysis-and-cleaning/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A Driver Script To Set Up A Data Analysis Pipeline</title>
				<description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In my previous post I reviewed a paper by Noble 2009 that proposed recommendations for best practice ways to set up a data analysis pipeline &lt;a href=&quot;http://ivanhanigan.github.io/2015/10/a-quick-review-of-a-quick-guide-to-organizing-computational-biology-projects/&quot;&gt;http://ivanhanigan.github.io/2015/10/a-quick-review-of-a-quick-guide-to-organizing-computational-biology-projects/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was following up on a series of posts I made about other best practice recommendations &lt;a href=&quot;http://ivanhanigan.github.io/2015/09/reproducible-research-and-managing-digital-assets-part-3/&quot;&gt;http://ivanhanigan.github.io/2015/09/reproducible-research-and-managing-digital-assets-part-3/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the paper by Noble it is suggested that a one should use a 'driver script' to automate creation of a directory structure, this is the exact way that &lt;code&gt;ProjectTemplate&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;makeProject&lt;/code&gt; work as I described them in the series of posts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I think Noble's framework offers something new to the recomendations I had canvassed, that is the idea of chronological order of the contents of the results directory.  I think this is an eminently sensible idea and thought that the R function &lt;code&gt;Sys.Date()&lt;/code&gt; would be a great way to start off a project in this way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;so I have put together the following R function, as an alternative to the &lt;code&gt;makeProject&lt;/code&gt; core function, that I thought I'd name so that there may be a family of makeProject functions, so that analysts have a range of to choose from.  The other candidate would be &lt;code&gt;makeProjectLong&lt;/code&gt;, which I will also put up before long.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;makeProjectNoble &amp;lt;- function(rootdir = getwd()){
  if(!exists(rootdir)) dir.create(rootdir)
  dir.create(file.path(rootdir,'doc'))
  dir.create(file.path(rootdir,'doc','paper'))
  sink(file.path(rootdir,'doc','workplan.Rmd'))
    cat(sprintf(&quot;---\ntitle: Untitled\nauthor: your name\ndate: %s\noutput: html_document\n---\n\n&quot;,
                Sys.Date()))
  sink()
  dir.create(file.path(rootdir,'data'))
  dir.create(file.path(rootdir,'data', Sys.Date()))
  dir.create(file.path(rootdir,'src'))
  dir.create(file.path(rootdir,'results')) 
  dir.create(file.path(rootdir,'results', Sys.Date())) 
  file.create(file.path(rootdir,'README.md'))
  }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Running this function will deploy the folders and files (I excluded the &lt;code&gt;bin&lt;/code&gt; folder for compiled binaries, as I believe that many data analysts may not need that, and those who do are geeky enough to write their own driver scripts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/testProjectNoble.png&quot; alt=&quot;/images/testProjectNoble.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Rmarkdown script is waiting for the analysis plan to be pumped out, and work can begin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/testProjectNobleMD.png&quot; alt=&quot;/images/testProjectNobleMD.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Noble, W. S. (2009). A quick guide to organizing computational biology projects. PLoS Computational Biology, 5(7), 1–5. &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000424&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000424&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<published>2015-10-12 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/10/a-driver-script-to-set-up-a-data-analysis-pipeline/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Coming To Grips With Citations In Reproducible Research Reports</title>
				<description>&lt;h1&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I was pleased to stumble on to Petr Keil\'s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.petrkeil.com/?p=2401&quot;&gt;Simple
template for scientific manuscripts in
Rmarkdown&lt;/a&gt; and the Github Repo
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/petrkeil/Blog/tree/master/2015_03_12_R_ms_template&quot;&gt;https://github.com/petrkeil/Blog/tree/master/2015_03_12_R_ms_template&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was already using Rmarkdown effectively for everything I wanted
except my bibliography, and this helped a lot.  But I eventually
found I needed to tweak the format of the citation style.  I tried
out a bunch of other CSL files but none felt just right.  I tried out
these after downloading from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/citation-style-language/styles&quot;&gt;https://github.com/citation-style-language/styles&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;american-physiological-society.csl
annals-of-the-association-of-american-geographers.csl
biomed-central.csl
ecology.csl
pnas.csl
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h1&gt;SO I hacked the CSL file&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I used the &lt;code&gt;american-physiological-society.csl&lt;/code&gt; to get stuff I wanted and pasted into the &lt;code&gt;mee.csl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get the files from this link &lt;a href=&quot;/rmarkdown_utils/CitationsInRmarkdown.Rmd&quot;&gt;/rmarkdown_utils/CitationsInRmarkdown.Rmd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get the files from this link &lt;a href=&quot;/rmarkdown_utils/meemodified.csl&quot;&gt;/rmarkdown_utils/meemodified.csl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get the files from this link &lt;a href=&quot;/rmarkdown_utils/refs.bib&quot;&gt;/rmarkdown_utils/refs.bib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;NB also that the csl file in petrkeil's repo is an older version from 2012 of the version in the citation-style repo called &lt;code&gt;methods-in-ecology-and-evolution&lt;/code&gt;.  The differences are not large though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;header-section-number&quot;&gt;1.1.1&lt;/span&gt; Example 1:&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The journal article by &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot;&gt;Michener et al. (1997)&lt;/span&gt; and another one &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot;&gt;(Bodnar &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; 2004)&lt;/span&gt; appear with their full URL even though I just want their DOI.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;header-section-number&quot;&gt;1.1.2&lt;/span&gt; Example 2:&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some recent papers &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot;&gt;(Open Science Collaboration 2015; Aiken &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; 2015; Davey &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; 2015)&lt;/span&gt; don’t have Volume info and I want to say [epub ahead of print].&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;header-section-number&quot;&gt;1.1.3&lt;/span&gt; Example 3:&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This blog post on ‘evidence based data analysis pipeline’ by &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot;&gt;Peng (2013)&lt;/span&gt; is one that definitely needs the URL and date accessed.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;h1&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Aiken, A.M., Davey, C., Hargreaves, J.R. &amp;amp; Hayes, R.J. (2015). Re-analysis of health and educational impacts of a school-based deworming programme in western Kenya: a pure replication. &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Epidemiology&lt;/em&gt;, dyv127. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://ije.oxfordjournals.org/content/early/2015/07/21/ije.dyv127.full http://www.ije.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/doi/10.1093/ije/dyv127&quot; class=&quot;uri&quot;&gt;http://ije.oxfordjournals.org/content/early/2015/07/21/ije.dyv127.full http://www.ije.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/doi/10.1093/ije/dyv127&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Bodnar, A., Castorina, R., Desai, M., Duramad, P., Fischer, S., Klepeis, N., Liang, S., Mehta, S., Naumoff, K., Noth, E.M., Schei, M., Tian, L., Vork, K.L. &amp;amp; Smith, K.R. (2004). Lessons learned from ‘the skeptical environmentalist’: an environmental health perspective. &lt;em&gt;International journal of hygiene and environmental health&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;207&lt;/strong&gt;, 57–67. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1438463904702643&quot; class=&quot;uri&quot;&gt;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1438463904702643&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Davey, C., Aiken, A.M., Hayes, R.J. &amp;amp; Hargreaves, J.R. (2015). Re-analysis of health and educational impacts of a school-based deworming programme in western Kenya: a statistical replication of a cluster quasi-randomized stepped-wedge trial. &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Epidemiology&lt;/em&gt;, dyv128. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://ije.oxfordjournals.org/content/early/2015/07/21/ije.dyv128.full http://www.ije.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/doi/10.1093/ije/dyv128&quot; class=&quot;uri&quot;&gt;http://ije.oxfordjournals.org/content/early/2015/07/21/ije.dyv128.full http://www.ije.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/doi/10.1093/ije/dyv128&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Michener, W.K., Brunt, J.W., Helly, J.J., Kirchner, T.B. &amp;amp; Stafford, S.G. (1997). Nongeospatial metadata for the ecological sciences. &lt;em&gt;Ecological Applications&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;7&lt;/strong&gt;, 330–342. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scopus.com/inward/record.url?scp=0030616825\&amp;amp;partnerID=8YFLogxK&quot; class=&quot;uri&quot;&gt;http://www.scopus.com/inward/record.url?scp=0030616825\&amp;amp;partnerID=8YFLogxK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Open Science Collaboration. (2015). Estimating the reproducibility of psychological science. &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;349&lt;/strong&gt;, aac4716–aac4716. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/doi/10.1126/science.aac4716&quot; class=&quot;uri&quot;&gt;http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/doi/10.1126/science.aac4716&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Peng, R.D. (2013). Implementing Evidence-based Data Analysis: Treading a New Path for Reproducible Research. &lt;em&gt;Simply statistics&lt;/em&gt;. Retrieved July 26, 2015, from &lt;a href=&quot;http://simplystatistics.org/2013/09/05/implementing-evidence-based-data-analysis-treading-a-new-path-for-reproducible-research-part-3/&quot; class=&quot;uri&quot;&gt;http://simplystatistics.org/2013/09/05/implementing-evidence-based-data-analysis-treading-a-new-path-for-reproducible-research-part-3/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# first replace the &amp;lt;macro name=&quot;access&quot;&amp;gt;
# with 
&amp;lt;macro name=&quot;access&quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;choose&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;if variable=&quot;DOI&quot;/&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;!--don't use if there is a DOI--&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;else&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;choose&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;if variable=&quot;URL&quot;&amp;gt;
          &amp;lt;group delimiter=&quot; &quot; prefix=&quot; &quot;&amp;gt;
            &amp;lt;group&amp;gt;
              &amp;lt;text variable=&quot;URL&quot;/&amp;gt;
            &amp;lt;/group&amp;gt;
            &amp;lt;group prefix=&quot;[&quot; suffix=&quot;]&quot; delimiter=&quot; &quot;&amp;gt;
              &amp;lt;date variable=&quot;accessed&quot;&amp;gt;
                &amp;lt;date-part name=&quot;day&quot;/&amp;gt;
                &amp;lt;date-part name=&quot;month&quot; prefix=&quot; &quot; suffix=&quot; &quot; form=&quot;short&quot;/&amp;gt;
                &amp;lt;date-part name=&quot;year&quot;/&amp;gt;
              &amp;lt;/date&amp;gt;
            &amp;lt;/group&amp;gt;
          &amp;lt;/group&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;/if&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;/choose&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/else&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/choose&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/macro&amp;gt;
#### Then add this ####
&amp;lt;macro name=&quot;date&quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;choose&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;if variable=&quot;issued&quot;&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;choose&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;if type=&quot;article-journal&quot;&amp;gt;
          &amp;lt;date variable=&quot;issued&quot;&amp;gt;
            &amp;lt;date-part name=&quot;year&quot;/&amp;gt;
          &amp;lt;/date&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;/if&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;else&amp;gt;
          &amp;lt;date variable=&quot;issued&quot;&amp;gt;
            &amp;lt;date-part name=&quot;year&quot;/&amp;gt;
          &amp;lt;/date&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;/else&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;/choose&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/if&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;else&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;text term=&quot;no date&quot; prefix=&quot;[&quot; suffix=&quot;]&quot;/&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/else&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/choose&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/macro&amp;gt;
#### And add this ####
      &amp;lt;else-if type=&quot;article-journal&quot;&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;choose&amp;gt;
          &amp;lt;if variable=&quot;issue volume&quot; match=&quot;any&quot;&amp;gt;
            &amp;lt;text macro=&quot;title&quot; suffix=&quot; &quot;/&amp;gt;
            &amp;lt;text variable=&quot;container-title&quot; suffix=&quot; &quot; form=&quot;short&quot; font-style=&quot;italic&quot; strip-periods=&quot;true&quot;/&amp;gt;
            &amp;lt;text variable=&quot;volume&quot;/&amp;gt;
            &amp;lt;text variable=&quot;page&quot; prefix=&quot;: &quot;/&amp;gt;
            &amp;lt;text macro=&quot;date&quot; prefix=&quot;, &quot; suffix=&quot;.&quot;/&amp;gt;
          &amp;lt;/if&amp;gt;
          &amp;lt;else&amp;gt;
            &amp;lt;choose&amp;gt;
              &amp;lt;if variable=&quot;DOI&quot;&amp;gt;
                &amp;lt;text macro=&quot;title&quot; suffix=&quot; &quot;/&amp;gt;
                &amp;lt;text variable=&quot;container-title&quot; suffix=&quot; &quot; form=&quot;short&quot; font-style=&quot;italic&quot;/&amp;gt;
                &amp;lt;group prefix=&quot;(&quot; suffix=&quot;).&quot;&amp;gt;
                  &amp;lt;date variable=&quot;issued&quot;&amp;gt;
                    &amp;lt;date-part name=&quot;month&quot; prefix=&quot; &quot; suffix=&quot; &quot;/&amp;gt;
                    &amp;lt;date-part name=&quot;day&quot; suffix=&quot;, &quot;/&amp;gt;
                    &amp;lt;date-part name=&quot;year&quot;/&amp;gt;
                  &amp;lt;/date&amp;gt;
                &amp;lt;/group&amp;gt;
                &amp;lt;text variable=&quot;DOI&quot; prefix=&quot; doi: &quot;/&amp;gt;
              &amp;lt;/if&amp;gt;
              &amp;lt;else&amp;gt;
                &amp;lt;text variable=&quot;container-title&quot; suffix=&quot;. &quot; form=&quot;short&quot; font-style=&quot;italic&quot;/&amp;gt;
              &amp;lt;/else&amp;gt;
            &amp;lt;/choose&amp;gt;
          &amp;lt;/else&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;/choose&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;/else-if&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Now use this modified csl in the header of the RMD file instead of mee.csl&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;header-section-number&quot;&gt;1.2&lt;/span&gt; NEW References&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Aiken, A.M., Davey, C., Hargreaves, J.R. &amp;amp; Hayes, R.J. (2015).Re-analysis of health and educational impacts of a school-based deworming programme in western Kenya: a pure replication &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Epidemiology&lt;/em&gt; (epub ahead of print July 2015). doi: &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyv127&quot;&gt;10.1093/ije/dyv127&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Bodnar, A., Castorina, R., Desai, M., Duramad, P., Fischer, S., Klepeis, N., Liang, S., Mehta, S., Naumoff, K., Noth, E.M., Schei, M., Tian, L., Vork, K.L. &amp;amp; Smith, K.R. (2004).Lessons learned from ‘the skeptical environmentalist’: an environmental health perspective. &lt;em&gt;International journal of hygiene and environmental health&lt;/em&gt; 207: 57–67, 2004.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Davey, C., Aiken, A.M., Hayes, R.J. &amp;amp; Hargreaves, J.R. (2015).Re-analysis of health and educational impacts of a school-based deworming programme in western Kenya: a statistical replication of a cluster quasi-randomized stepped-wedge trial &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Epidemiology&lt;/em&gt; (epub ahead of print July 2015). doi: &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyv128&quot;&gt;10.1093/ije/dyv128&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Michener, W.K., Brunt, J.W., Helly, J.J., Kirchner, T.B. &amp;amp; Stafford, S.G. (1997).Nongeospatial metadata for the ecological sciences &lt;em&gt;Ecological Applications&lt;/em&gt; 7: 330–342, 1997. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scopus.com/inward/record.url?scp=0030616825\&amp;amp;partnerID=8YFLogxK&quot;&gt;http://www.scopus.com/inward/record.url?scp=0030616825\&amp;amp;partnerID=8YFLogxK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Open Science Collaboration. (2015).Estimating the reproducibility of psychological science &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; 349: aac4716–aac4716, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Peng, R.D. (2013). Implementing Evidence-based Data Analysis: Treading a New Path for Reproducible Research. &lt;em&gt;Simply statistics&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://simplystatistics.org/2013/09/05/implementing-evidence-based-data-analysis-treading-a-new-path-for-reproducible-research-part-3/&quot;&gt;http://simplystatistics.org/2013/09/05/implementing-evidence-based-data-analysis-treading-a-new-path-for-reproducible-research-part-3/&lt;/a&gt; [26 Jul. 2015]&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<published>2015-10-09 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/10/coming-to-grips-with-citations-in-reproducible-research-reports/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A quick review of a quick guide to organizing computational biology projects</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The organisation of material is a particularly vexatious topic.  For a data analysis project it is very important that the set of folders and files is logical and intuitive, as well as being well documented. The oft-heard exhortation by computer scientists to their users to 'Read The F-ing Manual' (RTFM) is perennial and rooted in the fundamental difficulty of readers to have the time required to read and digest the detailed information there-in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In this post I review a paper that I was referred to by recent activity on the
Mozillascience studyGroupLesson 'Open Science Utility Belt':
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mozillascience/studyGroupLessons/issues/7&quot;&gt;https://github.com/mozillascience/studyGroupLessons/issues/7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That group also holds a journal club &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/minisciencegirl/studyGroup/issues/20#issuecomment-134750483&quot;&gt;https://github.com/minisciencegirl/studyGroup/issues/20#issuecomment-134750483&lt;/a&gt; and they reviewed this paper:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Noble, W. S. (2009). A quick guide to organizing computational biology projects. PLoS Computational Biology, 5(7), 1–5. &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000424&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000424&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I missed out so I thought I'd put my notes up here for reference:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;core guiding principle is simple: Someone unfamiliar with your project should be able to look at your computer files and understand in detail what you did and why&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your future self may find it difficult to understand your current work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Noble's law: 'Everything you do, you will probably have to do over again'&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;store all of the files relevant to one project in common root directory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The exception to this rule is data/code that are used in multiple projects, they are standalone projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Within a given project, use a top-level organization that is logical first, then chronological  at the next level, and then logical organization next&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Core folders are &lt;code&gt;data&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;results&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;doc&lt;/code&gt; (versus Berndt Weiss' &lt;code&gt;dat&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;ana&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;doc&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chronological order?  'tempting to apply a similar, logical organization... this approach is risky, because the logical structure of your final set of experiments may look drastically different from the form you initially designed. This is particularly true under the results directory, where you may not even know in advance what kinds of experiments you will need to perform'&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Recommended folder and file structures &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000424.g001&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000424.g001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;r&quot;&gt;/projectname (eg msms)/
    /doc/
        /ms-analysis.html 
        /paper/
            /msms.tex
            /msms.pdf
    /data/
        /YYYY-MM-DD/
            /yeast/
                /README
                /yeast.sqt
            /worm/
                /README
                /worm.sqt
    /src/
        /ms-analysis.c
    /bin/
        /parse-sqt.py
    /results/
        /notebook.html 
        /YYYY-MM-DD-1/
            /runall
            /split1/
            /split2/
        /YYYY-MM-DD-2/
            /runall
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a driver script to automate creation of a directory structure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maintain a chronologically organized lab notebook (I have been calling this a work 'log' sensu Scott Long's 2008 'Workflow book')&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create either a README file, or a command line driver script (he calls this &lt;code&gt;runall&lt;/code&gt;, but see also &lt;code&gt;main.R&lt;/code&gt; sensu the Reichian LCFD model)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you should end up with a file that is parallel to the lab notebook entry. The lab notebook contains a prose description of the exper- iment, whereas the driver script contains all the gory details&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Version Control.  'Nuff said! But how to build capacity with Github when all my colleagues seem so confused by it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</description>
				<published>2015-10-07 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/10/a-quick-review-of-a-quick-guide-to-organizing-computational-biology-projects/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Naming Conventions For Computer Files</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I'm working on a new Data Management Plan for a research group who
merge data from air pollution, meteorology, population census and
health outcome datasets.  The folder organisation is pretty much under
control now, but the file names are challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm searching for inspiration and was recommended this conversation:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/minisciencegirl/studyGroup/issues/20&quot;&gt;https://github.com/minisciencegirl/studyGroup/issues/20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;File Organization and Naming:
...
I want to include details of what the settings were or what dataset I
started out with. Rather than saving a file name a mile long
&quot;FlightHomLog2_av1_Euc_ArrayEucl_AvgLink&quot;, there must be many
different better ways to organizing my file space.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a bunch of good advice already here, and I recommend the slides &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Reproducible-Science-Curriculum/rr-organization1/tree/master/slides/naming-slides&quot;&gt;https://github.com/Reproducible-Science-Curriculum/rr-organization1/tree/master/slides/naming-slides&lt;/a&gt; and the two PLOS articles, but I wanted to pull out the two things I think it is important to get right:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ordering in lists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;substring chunks that can be extracted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think that the substring chunks are explained well in the slides link above (summary, use '_' or '-' to split the string), but I think that the ordering problem needs some thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tidy Data:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all reminds me of words from Hadley Wickham about tidy data, and the order that columns should be arranged in tabular data.  The principles are similar I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;&quot;&gt;A good ordering makes it easier to scan the raw values. One way of
organizing variables is by their role in the analysis: are values
fixed by the design of the data collection, or are they measured
during the course of the experiment? Fixed variables describe the
experimental design and are known in advance. Computer scientists
often call fixed variables dimensions, and statisticians usually
denote them with subscripts on random variables. Measured variables
are what we actually measure in the study. Fixed variables should come
first, followed by measured variables, each ordered so that related
variables are contiguous. Rows can then be ordered by the first
variable, breaking ties with the second and subsequent (fixed)
variables. 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Wickham, H. (2014). Tidy Data. JSS Journal of Statistical Software, 59(10).
Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jstatsoft.org/&quot;&gt;http://www.jstatsoft.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;One way that we did this:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colleagues and I came up with the following protocol for an ecology and biodiversity database&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Project name (optional sub-project name)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data type (such as experimental unit, observational unit, and/or measurement methods)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Geographic location (State, Country)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Temporal frequency and coverge Annual or seasonal tranches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Tidy data generalisable concepts are dimensions and variables&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of dimensions and variables can be useful here, and especially for deciding on filenames.  Dimensions are fixed or change slowly while variables change more quickly .  For example the project name is 'fixed', that is it does not change across the files, but the sub-project name does change, just more slowly (say there may be 2-3 different sub-projects within a project). Then there may be a set of data types, and these 'change' more quickly than the sub-project name (by change I mean, there are more of them).  Then the geographic and temporal variables might change quickest of all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a general rule for the order of things can be stated
The more fixed variables should come first (those things that don't change, or don't change much),
followed by the more fluid variables (or things that change more across the project).
List elements can then be ordered so that the groups of things that are similar will always be contiguous, and vary sequentially within clusters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps an example would be easier to understand.  Here is a set of file names that we constructed for one of our ecological field sites (project) and plots (sub-project or measurement location):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Notice we also had a controlled vocabulary of data types and their acronyms before starting this&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;| Filename                                                            | Title                                                                                                                                 |
|---------------------------------------------------------------------+---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------|
| asn_fnqr_soil_charact_robson_2011.csv                               | Soil Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2011                                                              |
| asn_fnqr_soil_pit_robson_2012.csv                                   | Soil Pit Data, Water Content and Temperature, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2012                           |
| asn_fnqr_veg_seedling_robson_2010-2012.csv                          | Seedling Survey,  Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2010-2012                                                  |
| asn_fnqr_veg_seedling_transect_coord_robson_2010-2012.csv           | Seedling Survey,  Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2010-2012                                                  |
| asn_fnqr_core_1ha_robson_2014.csv                                   | Soil Pit Data, Soil Characterisation, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha plot, 2014                   |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_biodiversity_ctbcc_2012.csv                          | Vertebrate Fauna Biodiversity Monitoring, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, CTBCC, 2012                                      |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_biodiversity_ctbcc_2013.csv                          | Vertebrate Fauna Biodiversity Monitoring, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, CTBCC, 2013                                      |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_biodiversity_ctbcc_capetrib_2014.csv                 | Avifauna Monitoring, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Cape Tribulation, 2014                                                |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_biodiversity_ctbcc_lu11a_2014.csv                    | Vertebrate Fauna Biodiversity Monitoring, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, CTBCC, LU11A, 2014                               |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_biodiversity_ctbcc_lu7a_2014.csv                     | Vertebrate Fauna Biodiversity Monitoring, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, CTBCC, LU7A, 2014                                |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_biodiversity_ctbcc_lu7b_2014.csv                     | Vertebrate Fauna Biodiversity Monitoring, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, CTBCC, LU7B, 2014                                |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_biodiversity_ctbcc_lu9a_2014.csv                     | Vertebrate Fauna Biodiversity Monitoring, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, CTBCC, LU9A, 2014                                |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_biodiversity_ctbcc-lu11a_2009-2011.csv               | Vertebrate Fauna Biodiversity Monitoring, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, CTBCC, LU11A, 2009-2011                          |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_biodiversity_ctbcc-lu7a_2009-2011.csv                | Vertebrate Fauna Biodiversity Monitoring, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, CTBCC, LU7A, 2009-2011                           |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_biodiversity_ctbcc-lu9a_2009-2011.csv                | Vertebrate Fauna Biodiversity Monitoring, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, CTBCC, LU9A, 2009-2011                           |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_biodiversity_habitat codes_ctbcc-lu11a_2009-2011.pdf | Vertebrate Fauna Biodiversity Monitoring, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, CTBCC, LU11A, 2009-2011                          |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_biodiversity_habitat codes_ctbcc-lu9a_2009-2011.pdf  | Vertebrate Fauna Biodiversity Monitoring, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, CTBCC, LU9A, 2009-2011                           |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_biodiversity_habitat_codes_ctbcc-lu7a_2009-2011.pdf  | Vertebrate Fauna Biodiversity Monitoring, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, CTBCC, LU7A, 2009-2011                           |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_birds_capture_robson_2011-2014.csv                   | Bird Capture Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2011-2014                                                 |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_birds_robson_2010-2014.csv                           | Bird Survey Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2010-2014                                                  |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_invert_moth_robson_2009.csv                          | Moth Inventory at Canopy and Ground Level, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2009                              |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_invert_moth_robson_2010.csv                          | Moth Inventory at Canopy and Ground Level, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2010                              |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_invert_moth_robson_2011.csv                          | Moth Inventory at Canopy and Ground Level, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2011                              |
| asn_fnqr_fauna_invert_robson_25ha_2013                              | Invertebrate Fauna Survey, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 25 Ha Plot, 2013                                  |
| asn_fnqr_geo_tracks_100m_grid_robson_2010-2013.kml                  | Base Geographical Data,  Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2010-2013                                           |
| asn_fnqr_geo_tracks_robson_2010-2013.kml                            | Base Geographical Data,  Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2010-2013                                           |
| asn_fnqr_geo_tracks_robson_2010-2013.mdb                            | Base Geographical Data,  Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2010-2013                                           |
| asn_fnqr_geo_tracks_trees_robson_2010-2013.kml                      | Base Geographical Data,  Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2010-2013                                           |
| asn_fnqr_soil_cosmos_robson_2011.csv                                | Soil Sampling for Calibration of Cosmic Ray Soil Moisture Sensor, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2011       |
| asn_fnqr_soil_pit_robson_2012.csv                                   | Soil Pit Data, Soil Characterisation, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2012                                   |
| asn_fnqr_soil_pit_robson_2013.csv                                   | Soil Pit Data, Water Content and Temperature, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2013                           |
| asn_fnqr_soil_properties_ddc_2013.csv                               | Soil Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Daintree Discovery Centre, 2013                                                 |
| asn_fnqr_soil_properties_ddc_2014.csv                               | Soil Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Daintree Discovery Centre, 2014                                                 |
| asn_fnqr_soil_properties_robson_2014.csv                            | Soil Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2014                                                              |
| asn_fnqr_stream_chem_robson_201310.csv                              | Water Chemistry Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 201310-201311                                          |
| asn_fnqr_stream_chem_robson_201310-201405.csv                       | Water Chemistry Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 201310-201405                                          |
| asn_fnqr_stream_chem_robson_201311.csv                              | Water Chemistry Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 201310-201311                                          |
| asn_fnqr_stream_chem_std_methods_robson_2013.pdf                    | Water Chemistry Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 201310-201311                                          |
| asn_fnqr_stream_phys-chem_diagram_robson_2013.pdf                   | Stream Physico-Chemical Data,  Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 201304-201305                                 |
| asn_fnqr_stream-phys-chem_robson_201304-201305.csv                  | Stream Physico-Chemical Data,  Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 201304-201305                                 |
| asn_fnqr_veg_cwd_robson_core_1ha_2012.csv                           | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha, 2012                                         |
| asn_fnqr_veg_dbh-h_capetrib_crane_plot_2001.csv                     | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Cape Tribulation, 1 ha Crane Plot, 2001                               |
| asn_fnqr_veg_dbh-h_capetrib_crane_plot_2005.csv                     | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Cape Tribulation, 1 ha Crane Plot, 2005                               |
| asn_fnqr_veg_dbh-h_capetrib_crane_plot_2010.csv                     | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Cape Tribulation, 1 ha Crane Plot, 2010                               |
| asn_fnqr_veg_dbh-h_robson_25ha_2009-2015.csv                        | Vascular Plant Data ÔëÑ 10 cm DBH,  Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 25 ha Plot, 2009-2015                    |
| asn_fnqr_veg_fruit_robson_25ha_2011-2015.csv                        | Fruit Phenology, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 25 ha Plot, 2011-2015                                       |
| asn_fnqr_veg_gentry_mid-stratum_robson_core_1ha_2012.csv            | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha, 2012                                         |
| asn_fnqr_veg_gentry_sub-stratum_herbs_robson_core_1ha_2012.csv      | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha, 2012                                         |
| asn_fnqr_veg_gentry_sub-stratum_shrubs_robson_core_1ha_2012.csv     | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha, 2012                                         |
| asn_fnqr_veg_lai_robson_core_1ha_2012.pdf                           | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha, 2012                                         |
| asn_fnqr_veg_leaf_phys_capetrib_20120831.csv                        | Leaf Level Physiology, Chemistry and Structural Traits, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Cape Tribulation, Crane Site, 2012 |
| asn_fnqr_veg_leaf_phys_master_aci_curves_robson_2012.csv            | Leaf Level Physiology, Chemistry and Structural Traits, Far North Queensland SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2012                            |
|                                                                     |                                                                                                                                       |
| asn_fnqr_veg_leaf_phys_master_ai_curves_robson_2012.csv             | Leaf Level Physiology, Chemistry and Structural Traits, Far North Queensland SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2012                            |
|                                                                     |                                                                                                                                       |
| asn_fnqr_veg_seedling_species_robson_2010-2012.csv                  | Seedling Survey,  Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2010-2012                                                  |
| asn_fnqr_veg_species_capetrib_crane_plot_2001.csv                   | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Cape Tribulation, 1 ha Crane Plot, 2001                               |
| asn_fnqr_veg_species_capetrib_crane_plot_2005.csv                   | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Cape Tribulation, 1 ha Crane Plot, 2005                               |
| asn_fnqr_veg_species_capetrib_crane_plot_2010.csv                   | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Cape Tribulation, 1 ha Crane Plot, 2010                               |
| asn_fnqr_veg_species_robson_2012.csv                                | Vegetation Species List, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2012                                                |
| asn_fnqr_veg_struct_robson_core_1ha_2012.csv                        | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha, 2012                                         |
| asn_fnqr_veg_struct_robson_core_1ha_centre_images_2012.zip          | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha, 2012                                         |
| asn_fnqr_veg_struct_robson_core_1ha_centre_images_2014.zip          | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha, 2012                                         |
| asn_fnqr_veg_struct_robson_core_1ha_ne_corner_images_2012.zip       | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha, 2012                                         |
| asn_fnqr_veg_struct_robson_core_1ha_ne_corner_images_2014.zip       | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha, 2012                                         |
| asn_fnqr_veg_struct_robson_core_1ha_nw_corner_images_2012.zip       | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha, 2012                                         |
| asn_fnqr_veg_struct_robson_core_1ha_nw_corner_images_2014.zip       | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha, 2012                                         |
| asn_fnqr_veg_struct_robson_core_1ha_se_corner_images_2012.zip       | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha, 2012                                         |
| asn_fnqr_veg_struct_robson_core_1ha_se_corner_images_2014.zip       | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha, 2012                                         |
| asn_fnqr_veg_struct_robson_core_1ha_sw_corner_images_2012.zip       | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha, 2012                                         |
| asn_fnqr_veg_struct_robson_core_1ha_sw_corner_images_2014.zip       | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha, 2012                                         |
| asn_fnqr_veg_structure_robson_core_1 ha.csv                         | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha, 2012                                         |
| asn_fnqr_veg_vascular plant list_robson_core_1 ha_2012.csv          | Vascular Plant Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, Core 1 ha, 2012                                         |
| asn_fnqr_water_properties_robson_2013.csv                           | Stream Physico-Chemical Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2013                                           |
| asn_fnqr_water_properties_robson_2014.csv                           | Stream Physico-Chemical Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2014                                           |
| asn_fnqr_weather_capetrib_2006.csv                                  | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Cape Tribulation, 2006                                               |
| asn_fnqr_weather_capetrib_2007.csv                                  | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Cape Tribulation, 2007                                               |
| asn_fnqr_weather_capetrib_2008.csv                                  | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Cape Tribulation, 2008                                               |
| asn_fnqr_weather_capetrib_2009.csv                                  | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Cape Tribulation, 2009                                               |
| asn_fnqr_weather_capetrib_2010.csv                                  | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Cape Tribulation, 2010                                               |
| asn_fnqr_weather_capetrib_2011.csv                                  | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Cape Tribulation, 2011                                               |
| asn_fnqr_weather_capetrib_2012.csv                                  | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Cape Tribulation, 2012                                               |
| asn_fnqr_weather_capetrib_2013.csv                                  | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Cape Tribulation, 2013                                               |
| asn_fnqr_weather_capetrib_2014.csv                                  | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Cape Tribulation, 2014                                               |
| asn_fnqr_weather_ddc_2008.csv                                       | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Daintree Discovery Centre, 2008                                      |
| asn_fnqr_weather_ddc_2009.csv                                       | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Daintree Discovery Centre, 2009                                      |
| asn_fnqr_weather_ddc_2010.csv                                       | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Daintree Discovery Centre, 2010                                      |
| asn_fnqr_weather_ddc_2011.csv                                       | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Daintree Discovery Centre, 2011                                      |
| asn_fnqr_weather_ddc_2012.csv                                       | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Daintree Discovery Centre, 2012                                      |
| asn_fnqr_weather_ddc_2013.csv                                       | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Daintree Discovery Centre, 2013                                      |
| asn_fnqr_weather_robson_2010.csv                                    | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2010                                                   |
| asn_fnqr_weather_robson_2011.csv                                    | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2011                                                   |
| asn_fnqr_weather_robson_2012.csv                                    | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2012                                                   |
| asn_fnqr_weather_robson_2013.csv                                    | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2013                                                   |
| asn_fnqr_weather_robson_2014.csv                                    | Weather Station Data, Far North Queensland Rainforest SuperSite, Robson Creek, 2014                                                   |
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
				<published>2015-10-05 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/10/naming-conventions-for-computer-files/</link>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>