<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>disentangle</title>
		<description>Disentangle Things</description>
		<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com</link>
		
			<item>
				<title>We have a statistically rigorous and scientifically meaningful definition of replication. Let's use it</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Researchers writing about the 'Reproducibility Crisis' often conflate
the terms reproducibility, repeatability and replicability, but it is
quite important to distinguish these.  There is a great discussion of
the distinction in the SimplyStatistics blog post titled: &lt;a href=&quot;http://simplystatistics.org/2015/10/20/we-need-a-statistically-rigorous-and-scientifically-meaningful-definition-of-replication&quot;&gt;We need a statistically rigorous and
scientifically meaningful definition of
replication&lt;/a&gt;.
But I actually now think &lt;em&gt;we DO have that definition!&lt;/em&gt; It is the
that repeatability is the same
as replication and involves a new sample with new measurement errors
while reproducibility uses the same data to recalculate the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is vital that we labour the point so that the
distinction between repeatability and reproducibility is made clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I follow the definition that 'reproducible' is exact re-computation
whereas repeatable/replicable is a new analysis, of a new sample,
yielding a new result (plus or minus some variance from measurement
error), and if the original study is replicated then the same
conclusions are reached from the new analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used this paragraph and recent reference in my thesis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Reproducibility is defined as ‘the ability to recompute data analytic
results given an observed dataset and knowledge of the data analysis
pipeline’ (Leek &amp;amp; Peng 2015). This definition distinguishes
reproducibility from replicability which is ‘the chance that an
independent experiment targeting the same scientific question will
produce a consistent result’ (Leek &amp;amp; Peng 2015).  

Leek, J.T. &amp;amp; Peng, R.D. (2015). Opinion: Reproducible research can
still be wrong: Adopting a prevention approach. Proceedings of the
National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 112(6),
1645–1646.  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I am also a big fan of the the definitions in Peng 2011 and Cassey 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peng 2011:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;With replication, independent investigators address a scientific
hypothesis and build up evidence for or against it...

Reproducibility calls for the data and computer code used to analyze
the data be made available to others. This standard falls short of
full replication because the same data are analysed again, rather than
analysing independently collected data.

Peng, R. D. (2011). Reproducible research in computational
science. Science, 334(6060), 1226–1227. doi:10.1126/science.1213847
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cassey 2006:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[For a repeatable study] a third party must be able to perform a study
using identical methodological proto- cols and analyze the resulting
data in an identical manner... [Further] a published result
must be presented in a manner that allows for a quantitative
comparison in a later study...

We consider a study reproducible if, from the information presented in
the study, a third party could replicate the re- ported results
identically. 

CASSEY, P., &amp;amp; BLACKBURN, T. M. (2006). Reproducibility and
Repeatability in Ecology. BioScience,
56(12), 958. doi:10.1641/0006-3568
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To fully endorse any scientific claims, the experimental findings should be completely repeatable by many independent investigators who ‘address areplicated hypothesis and build up evidence for or against it’ (Peng, 2011). It is important to note that the exact results need not be computed in a repeatable study. This is because experimentation involves probability, and if performed again, with a different sample and new set of measurement errors some variance between experiments is to be expected.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2016-01-12 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2016/01/we-have-a-statistically-rigorous-and-scientifically-meaningful-definition-of-replication/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Exemplars of distributing data and code - rOpenSci</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The practice of distributing data and code has a wide variety of possible approaches.  There are many resources available to be used to post data and code to the internet for dissemination, and it is very easy to access these resources.  It is more difficult to find exemplars of how data and code are easily and effectively distributed.  I am conducting a review of some of the resources that describe procedures for this and present exemplars in this and following notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A paper that describes the rOpenSci project's approach is &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.5334/jors.bu&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.5334/jors.bu&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;&quot;&gt;Boettiger, C., Chamberlain, S., Hart, E., &amp;amp; Ram,
K. (2015). Building Software, Building Community: Lessons from the
rOpenSci Project. Journal of Open Research Software,
3(1). 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper is focused on the way the community development and capacity building part of the project was conducted.  The diagram shown below is introduced as an example of the style that rOpenSci recommend a data analysis workflow be constructed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/workflow-ropensci.png&quot; alt=&quot;/images/workflow-ropensci.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus on publishing data to a public repository so early in the project (prior to final analysis and manuscript) seems premature to me. But then, I do feel that I am somewhat more concerned with vexatious activity by climate skeptics than the rOpenSci team.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2016-01-03 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2016/01/exemplars-of-distributing-data-and-code-ropensci/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>My framework of scientific workflow and integration software for holistic data analysis</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Scientific workflow and integration software for holistic data analysis (SWISH) is a
title I have given to describe the area of my research that focuses on the tools and techniques
of reproducible data analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reproducibility is the ability to recompute the results of a data
analysis with the original data.  It is possible to have analyses that
are reproducible with varying degrees of difficulty. A data
analysis might be reproducible but require thousands of hours of work to
piece together the datasets, transformations, manipulations, calculations and interpretations of computational results.
A primary challenge to reproducible data analysis is to make analyses
that are &lt;em&gt;easy&lt;/em&gt; to reproduce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve this, a guiding principle is that analysts should
effectively implement 'pipelines' of method steps and tools.  Data
analysts should employ standardised and evidence-based methods based
on conventions developed from many data analysts approaching the
problems in a similar way, rather than each analyst configuring
pipelines to suit particular individual or domain-specific
preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Planning and implementing a pipeline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be much easier to conceptualise a complicated data analysis
method than to implement this as a reproducible research pipeline. The
most effective way to implement a pipeline is by methodically tracking
each of the steps taken, the data inputs needed and all the outputs of
the step.  If done in a disciplined way then the analyst or some other
person could 'audit' the procedure easily and access the details of
the pipeline they need to scrutinise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Toward a standardised data analysis pipeline framework&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my own work I have tried a diverse variety of configurations based on
things I have read and discussions I have had.  Coming to the end of
my PhD project I have reflected on the framework that I have arrived at and
present this below as a schematic overview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;*   /home/
**    /overview.org 
           - summary data_inventory
           - DMP
**    /worklog.org    
           - YYYY-MM-DD
*   /projects/
**    /project1_data_analysis_project_health_research
***       /dataset1_merged_health_outcomes_and_exposures
             - index.org
             - git (local private, gitignore all subfolders)
             - workplan
             - worklog
             - workflow
             - main.Rmd
****         /data1_provided
****         /data2_derived
*****            - workflow script
****         /code
****         /results/  (this has all the pathways explored)
*****           - README.md
                 - git (public Github)
                 /YYYY-MM-DD-shortname (i.e. EDA, prelim, model-selection, sensitivity)
                     /main.Rmd
                     /code/
                     /data/
****         /report/
                   /manuscript.Rmd
                     - main results recomputed in production/publication quality
                     - supporting_information (but also can refer to github/results)
                 /figures_and_tables/
                     - png
                     - csv
*****           /journal_submission/
                     - cover letter
                     - approval signatures
                     - submitted manuscript
*****           /journal_revision/
                     - response.org
**    /project2_data_analysis_project_exposure_assessment
           - index.org
           - git
***       /dataset2.1_monitored_data
              - workplan
              - worklog
              - workflow
****         /data1_provided
****         /data2_derived 
                 - stored here or
                 - web2py crud or
                 - geoserver
              /data1_and_data2_backups
              /reports/
                 - manuscript.Rmd -&amp;gt; publish with the data somehow
              /tools (R package)
                 - git/master -&amp;gt; Github
****      /dataset2.2_GIS_layers 
**    /methods_or_literature_review_project
*  /tools/
         /web2py
             /applications
                 /data_inventory
                     - holdings
                     - prospective
                 /database_crud
          /disentangle (R package)
          /pipeline_templates
**   /data/
         /postgis_hanigan
         /postgis_anu_gislibrary
         /geoserver_anu_gislibrary
**   /references/
         - mendeley
         - bib
         - PDFs annotated
**   /KeplerData/workflows/MyWorkflows/
***      /data_analysis_workflow_using_kepler (implemented as an R package)
****         /inst/doc/A01_load.R
***      /data_analysis_workflow_using_kepler (implemented as an R LCFD workflow)
             - main.Rmd (raw R version)
             - main.xml (this is kepler)
****         /data/
                 - file1.csv
                 - file2.csv
****         /code/
                 - load.R
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
				<published>2015-12-22 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/12/my-framework-of-scientific-workflow-and-integration-software-for-holistic-data-analysis/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>This is an open notebook but selected content delayed</title>
				<description>&lt;h4&gt;Open Notebook Science, Selected Content, Delayed (ONS-SCD)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am trying to juggle my work in a dual Open-And-Closed way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explain: I try to keep an electronic ‘Open Notebook’ that aligns
with the principles of the Open Notebook Science (ONS) movement’s
‘Selected Content – Delayed’ category (ONS-SCD).  Back in 2012 when I started my notebook I looked
around for models of what style of publication I wanted.  I knew that some of my work was owned
by the university I work at, and I am not allowed to publish this openly.
Then there is other stuff I owned as part of my PhD, but that I might
not want to release all the details of my work.  So I settled on a 'Selected Content - Delayed' category and got the logo shown here from the (now-defunct) website &lt;a href=&quot;http://onsclaims.wikispaces.com/&quot;&gt;http://onsclaims.wikispaces.com/&lt;/a&gt;.  The ONS movement
is still described on Wikipedia though &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_notebook_science&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_notebook_science&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ONS-SCD.png&quot; alt=&quot;/images/ONS-SCD.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this publication model I
make publicly available the content of my research notebook (like a
blog), in which I write reports of the details of the data, code and
documents related to my research. I selectively make material open on
github, and I sometimes delay publication of the material that I keep
in my private research notebook.  That work is kept private either
because it includes unpublished work that I wish to keep embargoed
until after publication, or because it is all the gory details of
process of writing code to create or analyse data that is not
appropriate for open publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In previous work I have either paid for additional private repos on
github, and made the repo open once the paper is published, or
alternately used bitbucket with unlimited free private repos for
university students and then just put together a public repo for
sharing 'polished' outputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The upshot is that I use this part open / part closed approach during the data exploration, cleaning, analysis and writing. In my opinion as long as the final workflow is clearly and openly documented and reproducible, that's  the most important thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The motivation stems back to the Climategate scandal and infamous 'Harry Readme' file&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My supervisors over the years have all been really supportive of working in an open way and I have flirted with the idea of being completely open.  However, I got a little worried about the implications of working too openly when malicious people might dig though my work for vexatious reasons, such as looking for errors or embarrassing comments I might inadvertently make that, when taken out of context, might make me sound foolish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sounds far fetched, but as an example of this, a few years ago there was a fair amount of heat generated by a lot of
emails and other documents from the University of East Anglia Climate
Research University.  I was particularly interested because I was
struggling to make sense of a lot of weird and wonderful databases and
I felt a lot of sympathy for 'Harry', someone who as far as I could
tell was doing a pretty good job of exploring, cleaning and
documenting their work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is one journalists summary of this issue &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.telegraph.co.uk/technology/iandouglas/100004334/harry_read_me-txt-the-climategate-gun-that-does-not-smoke/&quot;&gt;http://blogs.telegraph.co.uk/technology/iandouglas/100004334/harry_read_me-txt-the-climategate-gun-that-does-not-smoke/&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
the contents of the harry_read_me.txt file, apparently leaked from the
University of East Anglia and now becoming a totem for climate change
sceptics to gather around as though it were a piece of the true cross.

This file – thousands of lines of annotations kept on the process of
re-developing a computer model of the climate form figures submitted
by weather stations around the world and other historical data sets –
holds a personal commentary written by an un-named developer (let's
call him Harry), frustrated and often tied up in knots, working late
into the night and the weekend trying to squeeze differently-formatted
numbers into a consistent narrative.  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Using git and Github in an ONS-SCD model&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recall Noble's framework?  The results folder is what I want to publish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Noble recommended the following folder and file structures &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000424.g001&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000424.g001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I revised his conceptual diagram, and I blogged about this at &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/10/a-quick-review-of-a-quick-guide-to-organizing-computational-biology-projects/&quot;&gt;/2015/10/a-quick-review-of-a-quick-guide-to-organizing-computational-biology-projects/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;/projectname (eg msms)/
    /doc/
        /ms-analysis.html 
        /paper/
            /msms.tex
            /msms.pdf
    /data/
        /YYYY-MM-DD/
            /yeast/
                /README
                /yeast.sqt
            /worm/
                /README
                /worm.sqt
    /src/
        /ms-analysis.c
    /bin/
        /parse-sqt.py
    /results/
        /notebook.html 
        /YYYY-MM-DD-1/
            /runall
            /split1/
            /split2/
        /YYYY-MM-DD-2/
            /runall
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;I want to publish my results, rather than my process&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I had the realisation that &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/10/how-to-effectively-implement-electronic-lab-notebooks-in-epidemiology/&quot;&gt;/2015/10/how-to-effectively-implement-electronic-lab-notebooks-in-epidemiology/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
    the 'Experiment Results' level is about work you might do on a 
       single day, or over a week

    Workflow scripts: At this level each 'experiment' is written up in
    chronological order, as entries to the Worklog at the meso level

    Noble recommends 'create either a README file, in which I store
    every command line that I used while performing the experi- ment,
    or a driver script (I usually call this runall) that carries out
    the entire experiment automatically'...

    and 'you should end up with a file that is parallel to the lab
    notebook entry. The lab notebook contains a prose description of
    the exper- iment, whereas the driver script contains all the gory
    details.'

    this is the level I usually think of managing the distribution
    side of things. I will want to pack up the results and email to my
    collaborators, or decide on the one set of tables and figures to
    write into the manuscript for submission to a journal. If this is
    accepted for publication, this is the one combined package of
    'analytical data and code' that I would consider putting up online
    (to github) as supporting information for the paper.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Public Github repo within a private local &lt;code&gt;overview&lt;/code&gt; git repo: My setup&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I mostly use one single Emacs orgmode file to run the whole project, using tangle to send chunks of code to scripts, after testing them out using the library of babel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To keep this version controlled I created a git repo for this&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To test out  have created a fake-data-analysis-project and this includes a local git repository&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in the &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt; file I added the commend &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; to ignore all subfolders and files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I want to add files to this I need to use &lt;code&gt;git add -f thefile&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then I create a public github repo in the results folder (I named the repo: &lt;code&gt;THE-PROJECT-NAME-results&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
$ cd ~/projects/fake-data-analysis-project
$ mkdir results
$ cd results/
/results$ git init
Initialized empty Git repository in /home/ivan_hanigan/tools/ReproducibleResearchPipelineTemplate/results/.git/
/results$ mkdir 2015-12-20-eda
/results$ git remote add origin git@github.com:ivanhanigan/ReproducibleResearchPipelineTemplate-results.git
$ git push -u origin master
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;The Result&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An example of these results are now published at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ivanhanigan/ReproducibleResearchPipelineTemplate-results&quot;&gt;https://github.com/ivanhanigan/ReproducibleResearchPipelineTemplate-results&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But the rest of my work is privately held, and version controlled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<published>2015-12-20 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/12/this-is-an-open-notebook-but-selected-content-delayed/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Using scholar rankings to provide weights in systematic literature reviews part 1</title>
				<description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've been thinking alot recently about an approach used in this recent systematic review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Vins, H., Bell, J., Saha, S., &amp;amp; Hess, J. (2015). The mental health
outcomes of drought: A systematic review and causal process
diagram. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public
Health, 12(10), 13251–13275. doi:10.3390/ijerph121013251
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They identify causal pathways from papers and ascribe the supporting evidentiary weight based on the number of papers published with findings that support this cause-effect pathway&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The raw number of papers is probably not a good metric, prone to bias so I was thinking of ways to ascribe weight based on quality of journal or authors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is not supposed to replace the need to actually read the papers, but purely as an additional source of information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This recent post on scholar metrics provided some impetus via h-indices
&lt;a href=&quot;http://datascienceplus.com/hindex-gindex-pubmed-rismed/&quot;&gt;http://datascienceplus.com/hindex-gindex-pubmed-rismed/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also think this approach of text mining the abstracts could be useful &lt;a href=&quot;http://tuxette.nathalievilla.org/?p=1682&quot;&gt;http://tuxette.nathalievilla.org/?p=1682&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Sanity check of the two options using myself as guinea pig&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;&quot;&gt;library(RISmed)
x &amp;lt;- &quot;hanigan+ic[Author]&quot;
res &amp;lt;- EUtilsSummary(x, type=&quot;esearch&quot;, db=&quot;pubmed&quot;, datetype='pdat', mindate=1900, 
  maxdate=2015, retmax=500)
str(res)
citations1 &amp;lt;- Cited(res)
citations &amp;lt;- as.data.frame(citations1)
citations &amp;lt;- citations[order(citations$citations,decreasing=TRUE),]
citations &amp;lt;- as.data.frame(citations)
str(citations)
citations &amp;lt;- cbind(id=rownames(citations),citations)
citations$id&amp;lt;- as.character(citations$id)
citations$id&amp;lt;- as.numeric(citations$id)
hindex &amp;lt;- max(which(citations$id&amp;lt;=citations$citations))

hindex
# 5

library(scholar)
myid &amp;lt;- &quot;cGN1P0wAAAAJ&quot;
y &amp;lt;- scholar::get_publications(myid)
str(y)
y[,c(&quot;author&quot;, &quot;cites&quot;)]
y$id &amp;lt;- as.numeric(row.names(y))
hindex2 &amp;lt;- max(which(y$id&amp;lt;=y$cites))
hindex2
# 15
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Clearly the pubmed and google scholar search engines makes a big difference to my score!&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
				<published>2015-12-17 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/12/using-scholar-rankings-to-provide-weights-in-systematic-literature-reviews-part-1/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>My project inventory</title>
				<description>&lt;h3&gt;Auditing and inventorising&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I just completed an audit of my project files and updated the list on my website &lt;a href=&quot;/projects.html&quot;&gt;http://ivanhanigan.github.com/projects.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was enabled by the work I have been doing on a data inventory web2py app &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ivanhanigan/data_inventory&quot;&gt;https://github.com/ivanhanigan/data_inventory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The list shows some of the project data collections I have amassed during my research over the last 15 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some of these are data collections I have developed, others are derivatives of collections originated by others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many of these are areas of active research, but others are dormant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This list will be updated as time permits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Projects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 Air pollution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 Australian health&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 Australian population&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 Biodiversity and environmental change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 Bioregions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6 Cardio-respiratory disease, biomass smoke, dust and heatwaves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7 Climate Change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8 Eco-social observatories&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9 Extreme Weather Events&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10 GIS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11 Infectious diseases and local habitat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12 Mental health and drought&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;13 Mortality and morbidity effects from weather&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;14 Reproducible research pipelines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15 Medical geography theory and tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;16 Roads and places&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;17 Transformational adaptation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;18 Ultraviolet radiation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;19 Water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;20 Weather&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<published>2015-12-07 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/12/my-project-inventory/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>show-missingness-in-large-dataframes-with-ggplot-thanks-to-r-blogger</title>
				<description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is a revision of my post &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/10/show-missingness-in-large-dataframes-v2&quot;&gt;/2015/10/show-missingness-in-large-dataframes-v2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This guy posted &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.njtierney.com/r/missing%20data/rbloggers/2015/12/01/ggplot-missing-data/&quot;&gt;http://www.njtierney.com/r/missing%20data/rbloggers/2015/12/01/ggplot-missing-data/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Let's try it out!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(devtools)
# depends
install.packages(&quot;gbm&quot;)
install_github(&quot;tierneyn/neato&quot;)
library(neato)
# small eg
locs=c(&quot;Australia&quot;,&quot;India&quot;,&quot;New Zealand&quot;,&quot;Sri Lanka&quot;,&quot;Uruguay&quot;,&quot;Somalia&quot;)
f1=c(T,F,T,T,F,F)
f2=c(F,F,F,T,F,F)
f3=c(F,T,T,T,F,T)
atable=data.frame(locs,f1,f2,f3)
atable[atable == FALSE] &amp;lt;- NA
atable
png(&quot;ggplotmissing.png&quot;)
ggplot_missing(atable)
dev.off()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ggplotmissing.png&quot; alt=&quot;/images/ggplotmissing.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The one I had problems with because too large is:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Cool but what about a big one?
dat &amp;lt;- read.csv(&quot;~/path/to/file.csv&quot;)
str(dat)
png(&quot;ggplotmissing2.png&quot;, height=1800, width = 3000, res = 200)
ggplot_missing(dat)
dev.off()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ggplotmissing2.png&quot; alt=&quot;/images/ggplotmissing2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2015-12-02 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/12/show-missingness-in-large-dataframes-with-ggplot-thanks-to-r-blogger/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Notes from Dr Climate Re data reference syntax models for file organisation and naming</title>
				<description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is an excellent explanation of the Australian Integrated Marine Observing System (IMOS) Data Reference Syntax by Damien Irving on the Dr Climate blog  &lt;a href=&quot;https://drclimate.wordpress.com/2015/09/04/managing-your-data/&quot;&gt;https://drclimate.wordpress.com/2015/09/04/managing-your-data/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Data Reference Syntax (DRS) – a convention for naming your files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;computer&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;project&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;organisation&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;collection&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;facility&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;data-type&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;site-code&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;year&amp;gt;/

The data type has a sub-DRS of its own, which tells us that the data
represents the 1-hourly average surface current for a single month
(October 2012), and that it is archived on a regularly spaced spatial
grid and has not been quality controlled.

Just in case the file gets separated from this informative directory
structure, much of the information is repeated in the file name
itself, along with some more detailed information about the start and
end time of the data, and the last time the file was modified:

&amp;lt;project&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;facility&amp;gt;_V_&amp;lt;time-start&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;site-code&amp;gt;_FV00_&amp;lt;data-type&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;time-end&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;modified&amp;gt;.nc.gz

In the first instance this level of detail seems like a bit of
overkill... 

Since the data are so well labelled,
locating all monthly timescale ACORN data from the Turquoise Coast and
Rottnest Shelf sites (which represents hundreds of files) would be as
simple as typing the following at the command line:

$ ls */ACORN/monthly_*/{TURQ,ROT}/*/*.nc
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Damien's personalised DRS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is worthwhile thinking through these ideas and incorporating them in ones data management system as early as possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Damien has also helpfully openly shared his own DRS at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/DamienIrving/climate-analysis/blob/master/data_reference_syntax.md&quot;&gt;https://github.com/DamienIrving/climate-analysis/blob/master/data_reference_syntax.md&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Here is a summary of some key items I'm going to implement versions of for my own work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Basic data files&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;var&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;dataset&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;level&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;time&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;spatial&amp;gt;.nc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sub-categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;time&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;tstep&amp;gt;-&amp;lt;aggregation&amp;gt;-&amp;lt;season&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;spatial&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;grid&amp;gt;-&amp;lt;region&amp;gt;-&amp;lt;bounds&amp;gt;-&amp;lt;np&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Where:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;tstep&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;daily&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;monthly&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;aggregation&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;030day-runmean&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;anom-wrt-1979-2011&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;anom-wrt-all&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;season&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;JJA&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;MJJASO&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;grid&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;native&lt;/code&gt; or something like &lt;code&gt;y181x360&lt;/code&gt;, which describes the number of latitude (181) and longitude (360) points (in this case it is a 1 by 1 degree horizontal grid).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;region&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: Region names are defined in &lt;code&gt;netcdf_io.py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;bounds&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: e.g. &lt;code&gt;lon225E335E-lat10S10N&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;mermax&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;zonal-anom&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;np&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: North pole location, e.g. &lt;code&gt;np20N260E&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Examples include:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;code&gt;psl_Merra_surface_daily_y181x360.nc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More complex file names&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;inside&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;filters&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;prev-var&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;dataset&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;level&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;time&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;spatial&amp;gt;.nc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sub-categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;inside&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: The variable inside the file. e.g. &lt;code&gt;tas-composite&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;datelist&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;filters&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: e.g. &lt;code&gt;samgt90pct&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;code&gt;gt&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;lt&lt;/code&gt; and used for greater and less than, &lt;code&gt;pct&lt;/code&gt; for percentile)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;prev-var&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: if it's not obvious what variable &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;inside&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; was created from, include the previous variable/s&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Examples:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;code&gt;tas-composite_pwigt90pct_ERAInterim_500hPa_030day-runmean-anom-wrt-all_native-sh.png&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Principles of Tidy Data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the words of Hadley Wickham the order that data should be
arranged in follows some generic principles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;'A good ordering makes it easier to scan the raw values. One way of
organizing variables is by their role in the analysis: are values
fixed by the design of the data collection, or are they measured
during the course of the experiment? Fixed variables describe the
experimental design and are known in advance. Computer scientists
often call fixed variables dimensions, and statisticians usually
denote them with subscripts on random variables. Measured variables
are what we actually measure in the study. Fixed variables should come
first, followed by measured variables, each ordered so that related
variables are contiguous. Rows can then be ordered by the first
variable, breaking ties with the second and subsequent (fixed)
variables.'
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;An exemplar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my last project the protocol we developed (for an ecology and biodiversity database) had a naming convention which relied heavily on a sequence of information being used to order the names of folders, subfolders and files.  This is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The project name (and optional sub-project name)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data type (such as experimental unit, observational unit, and/or measurement methods)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Geographic location (locality name, State, Country)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Temporal frequency and coverage (such as annual or seasonal tranches).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The concepts of slow moving dimensions and fast moving variables&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of dimensions and variables can be useful here, and especially for deciding on filenames.  Dimensions are fixed or change slowly while variables change more quickly.  By 'change', this  means that there are more of them. For example the project name is 'fixed', that is it does not change across the files, but the sub-project name does change, just more slowly (say there may be 2-3 different sub-projects within a project). Then there may be a set of data types, and these 'change' more quickly than the sub-project name.  Then the geographic and temporal variables might change quickest of all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a general rule for the order of things can be stated. The fixed and slowly changing variables should come first (those things that don't change, or don't change much),
followed by the more fluid variables (or things that change more across the project).
List elements can then be ordered so that the groups of things that are similar will always be contiguous, and vary sequentially within clusters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the only thing I disagree with Damien about is his decision to put space after time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;var&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;dataset&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;level&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;time&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;spatial&amp;gt;.nc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is  because I think that the geography is more stable than the time period for a data collection, and as most of my studies look at changes of variables measured at a location over time I generally want to compare the same spot at multiple times.  There are pros and cons of each approach such as if the analyst wants to make maps of a variable measured at several locations at a single point in time then having the data arranged by time first and then location may make that job simpler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also notice however that the IMOS syntax puts the site spatial location before the year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2015-11-29 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/11/notes-from-dr-climate-re-data-reference-syntax-models-for-file-organisation-and-naming/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Visualisation tools for communicating data management concepts</title>
				<description>&lt;h1&gt;Hyperlinked table of contents that looks like a filing system&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This looks like it might be useful to display information about filing systems, with a clickable toc that looks like a filing system!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tex.stackexchange.com/a/36185&quot;&gt;http://tex.stackexchange.com/a/36185&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;object data=&quot;/images/tikz_hlink.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;800&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Alternative text - include a link &lt;a href=&quot;images/tikz_hlink.pdf&quot;&gt;to the PDF!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;

</description>
				<published>2015-11-26 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/11/visualisation-tools-for-communicating-data-management-concepts/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A picture of the newnode function for workflow visualisation in R</title>
				<description>&lt;h2&gt;Newnode: An R function for visualising workflows&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scientific workflow concept is essentially a pipeline.  The method step is the key atomic unit of a scientific pipeline.  It consists of inputs, outputs and a rationale for why the step is taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple way to keep track of the steps, inputs and outputs is shown in Table below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;CLUSTER ,  STEP       , INPUTS                   , OUTPUTS                   
A  ,       Step1      , &quot;Input 1, Input 2&quot;       , Output 1                 
A  ,       Step2      ,  Input 3                 , Output 2                   
B  ,       Step3      , &quot;Output 1, Output 2&quot;     , Output 3                  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The steps and data listed in this way can be visualised.
To achieve this an R function was written as part of my PhD project and is distributed in the R package available on Github &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ivanhanigan/disentangle&quot;&gt;https://github.com/ivanhanigan/disentangle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the &lt;code&gt;newnode&lt;/code&gt; function.  The function returns a string of text
written in the &lt;code&gt;dot&lt;/code&gt; language which can be rendered in R using the
&lt;code&gt;DiagrammeR&lt;/code&gt; package, or the standalone &lt;code&gt;graphviz&lt;/code&gt; package.   This creates the graph of this pipeline shown in Figure below.  Note that a new field was added for Descriptions as these are highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/steps_basic_rstudio-test.png&quot; alt=&quot;/images/steps_basic_rstudio-test.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2015-11-17 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/11/a-picture-of-the-newnode-function-for-workflow-visualisation-in-r/</link>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>