<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>disentangle</title>
		<description>Disentangle Things</description>
		<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com</link>
		
			<item>
				<title>Time series regression in R course codes for Chicago Heatwave</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I am giving a talk and R demonstration tomorrow for the Epidemiology Special Interest Group (EPISIG) on Time series regression in R for heat and heatwave analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope some of the audience will bring their laptop and use install.packages('dlnm') to follow along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are links to the training resources I will use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Distributed Lag Non-Linear Models (DLNM) package + recent “TSCOURSE”:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Antonio Gasparrini, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CAR Workshop “Advanced modelling techniques for time series analysis using R”. Woolcock
Institute, Sydney - 05 April 2019. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ag-myresearch.com/tscourse.html&quot;&gt;http://www.ag-myresearch.com/tscourse.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Online tutorial for Climate Change impact assessment in London
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gasparrini/2019_vicedo-cabrera_Epidem_Rcodedata&quot;&gt;https://github.com/gasparrini/2019_vicedo-cabrera_Epidem_Rcodedata&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Codes for today’s talk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I modified the TSCOURSE codes from London CO to Chicago heatwave
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ivanhanigan/spatiotemporal-multilevel-models/blob/master/4_2_time_series_analysis/tscourse-chicago.R&quot;&gt;https://github.com/ivanhanigan/spatiotemporal-multilevel-models/blob/master/4_2_time_series_analysis/tscourse-chicago.R&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your laptop doesn’t have R or R-studio try &lt;a href=&quot;https://coesra.tern.org.au&quot;&gt;https://coesra.tern.org.au&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<published>2019-07-04 00:00:00 +1000</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2019/07/tscourse-chicago-heatwave/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Climate Change policy inaction threatens lives</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Today we are launching &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mja.com.au/journal/2018/209/11/mja-lancet-countdown-health-and-climate-change-australian-policy-inaction?utm_source=carousel&amp;amp;utm_medium=web&amp;amp;utm_campaign=homepage&quot;&gt;a new Australian climate change and health paper&lt;/a&gt; that I'm involved with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Zhang Y, Beggs PJ, Bambrick H, Berry HL, Linnenluecke MK, Trueck S,
Alders R, Bi P, Boylan SM, Green D, Guo Y, Hanigan IC, Hanna EG, Malik
A, Morgan GG, Stevenson M, Tong S, Watts N, Capon AG. The MJA–Lancet
Countdown on health and climate change: Australian policy inaction
threatens lives. The Medical Journal of Australia
2018;209(11):1.e1- 1.e21. doi: 10.5694/mja18.00789.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, the release of the related Global edition is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tinyurl.com/ya76m2nl&quot;&gt;Lancet Countdown 2018 Report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that the &quot;Australian policy inaction threatens lives&quot; theme may reappear under a number of guises.
Still, at least we are in the bandwagon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team amassed data on a large range of indicators that we put together to show the current impacts of climate change, from deaths due to human-made air pollution, lethal extreme weather events, infectious mosquito borne diseases and the public awareness of climate change issues and policies. We intend to re-visit these indicators regularly each year and track the ongoing developments of these emerging public health issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Events will be today at Sydney University TODAY and tomorrow Fri 30th 3pm Canberra launch event that I'm going to. Our Ministers Fitzharris and Rattenbury will be there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is too late to RSVP for the Sydney event but RSVP by 29 November to Christian Dent at rattenbury@act.gov.au
for the Canberra event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time: 3pm, 30 November, 2018, followed by Reception
Venue: Exhibition Room, Legislative Assembly Building, Canberra&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2018-11-29 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2018/11/climate-change-policy-inaction-threatens-lives/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>IUCN Red List Ecosystems Framework Applicability To Health Impact Assessments</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago I was fortunate to work on an IUCN Red List of Ecosystems project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guru, S., Hanigan, I. C., Nguyen, H. A., Burns, E., Stein, J., Blanchard, W., … Clancy, T. (2016). Development of a cloud-based platform for reproducible science: A case study of an IUCN Red List of Ecosystems Assessment. Ecological Informatics, 36, 221–230. &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoinf.2016.08.003&quot;&gt;http://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoinf.2016.08.003&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is based on a well thought through framework:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The original exposition for IUCN ecosystem risk assessments was set out in Keith, D. A., Rodríguez, J. P., Rodríguez-Clark, K. M., Nicholson, E., Aapala, K., Alonso, A., … Zambrano-Martínez, S. (2013). Scientific Foundations for an IUCN Red List of Ecosystems. PLoS ONE, 8(5). &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0062111&quot;&gt;http://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0062111&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is an associated guidelines for a  Risk Assessment outlined in Rodriguez, J. P., Keith, D. a., Rodriguez-Clark, K. M., Murray, N. J., Nicholson, E., Regan, T. J., … Wit, P. (2015). A practical guide to the application of the IUCN Red List of Ecosystems criteria S2. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences, 370(1662), 20140003–20140003. &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2014.0003&quot;&gt;http://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2014.0003&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have recently been reminded in several instances of the overlap with Health Impact Assessments, especially in complex eco-social contexts, and when stakes are high (so if one risk factor is critical the entire assessment gets that level of risk) and where data are not available (the use of the Data Deficient category).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth thinking of when can't achieve data quality or dose-response and/or base-line prevalence required for Burden of Disease methodological 'purity'.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The options in addition to main criteria (Critically Endangered –&gt; Vulnerable -&gt; Least concern) are: Data Deficient, Not Evaluated and Near Threatened (scoring close to the threshold). Overall threat status is the highest level of risk on any of the 5 criteria.  We ended up using DD a lot, but still get pretty good assessments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final note: the work I did led me to re-order the sequence of steps from the implied order of the Criteria A, B, C, D and E.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practice it makes more sense to start at Criterion D 'the Primary Biotic Variable', because defining this at the outset means that there are many fewer potential variables to actually include (because ecosystems are big and complicated things with many possible biotic variables of interest). This gives the whole assessment a focus and targetted feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in my work I did this sequence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Criterion D The primary biotic variable&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do this first! This allows the scope of the assessment to be defined around a particular set of key biological and abiotic attributes of the ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This requires an assessment for three time periods of the response of the principal biotic variable:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;D1 computes the disruption over the past 50 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;D2 describes the projected disruption of the next 50 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;D3 computes the disruption since 1750&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h1&gt;Criterion E The probability of ecosystem collapse&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing this second means that if there is any indication that this ecosystem is in peril then you can immediately classify it as &quot;Critical&quot; and not worry about doing any of the other steps.  Just get on witht he job of saving it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Criterion E is an overarching analysis of the impacts of biotic variables on the probability of ecosystem collapse within 50–100 years. We ran simulations to investigate the future resource&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Criterion A Decline in ecosystem distribution&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also done at three time periods:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A1) Decline in distribution current (past 50 years)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A2) Future decline (a) next 50 yrs or (b) any 50 year includes present and future&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A3) Historic decline (decline since 1750)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Don't be afraid to use the &quot;Data Deficient&quot; category here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Criterion B Restricted distribution&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;B1 extent (convex hull around observed occurences) AND ANY a) decline, b) threat, OR c) small N &quot;locations&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;B2 area of occupancy AND any a-c (assessed within 10km2 grid cells)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;B3 small N locations AND threats in short term (ie in the case of a mega landscape fire we have: burnt and unburnt = 2 locations)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;NB &quot;Locations&quot; are those discrete areas of the ecosystem that would be affected by the most pervasive plausible threat (ie wildfire).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Criterion C Decline in abiotic processes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important abiotic variables are Temperature and precipitation and other climate-related variables were used for Criterion C&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C1 past 50&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C2 next 50 IPCC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C3 since 1750&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<published>2018-03-29 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2018/03/iucn-red-list-ecosystems-framework-applicability-to-health/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Australian Air National Environment Protection Measure (NEPM) is about protecting human health</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;In Australia the Air Quality NEPMS &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.legislation.gov.au/Details/C2004H03935&quot;&gt;https://www.legislation.gov.au/Details/C2004H03935&lt;/a&gt; are a measure &quot;to be implemented by the laws and other arrangements participating jurisdictions consider necessary&quot;.
Performance against the Air NEPM is assessed at compliance stations located at sites representative of air quality likely to be experienced by the general population.
Australia has had national standards and goals for ambient air quality since 1998 (althought the harmful fine particulates (PM2.5) was added in the 2016 revisions to the Air NEPM, to be reported on annually from June 2018).
The Air NEPM mandates a consistent approach to air quality monitoring, which has been applied by all states and territories, but — recognising the different legislative arrangements in each jurisdiction — does not dictate the means to be applied to achieve the goals. Performance against the standards and goals is published annually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent unsuccessful grant application of mine, a reviewer commented that I had a lack of understanding of the process of the development of the standards and asserted:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&quot;1) the criteria are not health-based as such, and the regulatory
policy decisions are not all about minimising health impact&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&quot;2) the NEPM for ambient air quality only provides for ambient air
quality that allows for the &quot;adequate&quot; protection of human health
and well-being&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This reviewer makes the assertion that &quot;adequate&quot; protection of health is not the same as &quot;minimising health impact&quot;.
I guess the argument is that an &quot;adequate&quot; minimum level of health impact should consider a balance between the costs of expenditure on continued reductions in emissions against the benefits to health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I think that the criteria ARE health-based, and that the NEPM IS about minimising human health impacts (with the caveat that this is in the context of an economic cost-benefit assessment).
For example in the US &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.colorado.gov/pacific/performancemanagement/ensure-air-quality-improved-and-protected-reducing-air-pollution-across-colorado&quot;&gt;Colorado&lt;/a&gt; continually strives to reduce air pollutant emissions in ways that ensure public health and environmental protections, &lt;em&gt;while maintaining a vibrant economy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a cost-benefit analysis was included in my grant application, and I argue that this is vital to equip state Environmental Protection Authorities (EPA) with metrics to inform interventions. Such interventions are needed as Australian governments try to achieve the National Clean Air Agreement (made between the Commonwealth and each state and territory jurisdictions) which aims to implement strengthened laws that move to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.environment.gov.au/protection/air-quality/national-clean-air-agreement&quot;&gt;even tighter standards in 2025&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2018-02-20 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2018/02/the-aus-air-pollution-nepm-is-about-protecting-human-health/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Filling empty cells in columns with R</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Happy new year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have had a bit of a break and caught up with some of the older blog posts I did not find time for earlier in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one caught my eye: &lt;a href=&quot;http://varianceexplained.org/r/start-blog/&quot;&gt;http://varianceexplained.org/r/start-blog/&lt;/a&gt; especially the line 'When you’ve given the same advice 3 times, write a blog post'. So I thought I'd write a blog post about a bit of R code advice. (Disclaimer: This wasn't originally my work, but I used this advice more than 3 times, so am sharing here. This is a function I got from my colleague Phil TnT).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some cases I get data in a table that simplifies the presentation by only labelling one row in a set of rows like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
   person        fruit    suburb something
      Tom      oranges   Scullin       &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;3.0&lt;/span&gt;
                apples                 &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;6.0&lt;/span&gt;
                 pears                 &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;9.0&lt;/span&gt;
              tim tams                 &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2.0&lt;/span&gt;
 Gertrude       durian Charnwood       &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;3.7&lt;/span&gt;
          dragon fruit                 &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;7.0&lt;/span&gt;
               lychees                 &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;4.9&lt;/span&gt;
             pineapple               &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;100.9&lt;/span&gt;
                apples                &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;98.0&lt;/span&gt;
Pennelope      cashews   Higgins       &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2.0&lt;/span&gt;
             beer nuts                 &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;5.6&lt;/span&gt;
              Pringles                 &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;4.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use this like tidy data we need to fill these intervening cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;fill.col &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kr&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;x&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; col.name&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      s &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;which&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;x&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt;col.name&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      item &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; x&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt;col.name&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]][&lt;/span&gt;s&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
      hold &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;vector&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;list&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;length&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;item&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;br/&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;kr&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;i &lt;span class=&quot;kr&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;length&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;hold&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; hold&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt;i&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;rep&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;item&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;i&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;is.na&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;s&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;i&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;+1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;dim&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;x&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; s&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;i&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;+1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; s&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;i&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
      x&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt;col.name&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;unlist&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;hold&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      x
      &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;d &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; fill.col&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;d&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;person&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
fill.col&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;d&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;suburb&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  person        fruit    suburb something
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;        Tom      oranges   Scullin       &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;3.0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;        Tom       apples   Scullin       &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;6.0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;        Tom        pears   Scullin       &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;9.0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;        Tom     tim tams   Scullin       &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2.0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;   Gertrude       durian Charnwood       &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;3.7&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;   Gertrude dragon fruit Charnwood       &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;7.0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;   Gertrude      lychees Charnwood       &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;4.9&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;   Gertrude    pineapple Charnwood     &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;100.9&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;9&lt;/span&gt;   Gertrude       apples Charnwood      &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;98.0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt; Pennelope      cashews   Higgins       &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2.0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt; Pennelope    beer nuts   Higgins       &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;5.6&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt; Pennelope     Pringles   Higgins       &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;4.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2017-12-31 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2017/12/fillcolumns-in-R/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>My view of the research data analysis pipeline</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I put these ideas down when I gave a talk for the Aust National Data Service (ANDS) training course for data librarians at universities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finding out about data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Putting data somewhere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doing stuff with data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finding out what has been done with data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sharing data with others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suggest that the future needs actions that support each of these activities at the following levels:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Individual researcher&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research group&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research centre&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Faculty/Institute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;University&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-university collaborative groups (e.g. CRC or CRE)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The government and private sectors may have some similarities, but I don't know.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2017-12-07 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2017/12/my-view-of-the-research-data-analysis-pipeline/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The impact of scale on associations between disadvantage and hospitalization for heart diseases</title>
				<description>&lt;h1&gt;Disadvantage and disease hidden in plain sight: University of Canberra study&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disease mapping has been used as a modern tool for identifying risks and informing public health policy, but researchers at the University of Canberra say the real story of socio-economic disadvantage and disease is often hidden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;University of Canberra Health Research Institute (HRI) research shows that often the wrong geographical scale is being used for disease mapping which obscures the statistical associations of risks and health outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These findings are part of HRI’s Impact of scale of aggregation on associations of cardiovascular hospitalization and socio-economic disadvantage paper which has been published on 29 November 2017 in the journal PLOS One &lt;a href=&quot;http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0188161&quot;&gt;http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0188161&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HRI’s data scientist and lead author of the report, Dr Ivan Hanigan, said that “in order to protect the anonymity of health data, government authorities prefer large scale mapping, which impacts the evidence they need for policy responses. It’s left them with little detail and a picture that doesn’t reflect reality,” Dr Hanigan said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The salt-and-pepper approach to Canberra’s public housing and high-density living, which means low socio-economic groups are spread out throughout the city’s suburbs, hides the disadvantage when studied at certain scales. Current disease mapping often shows a uniform level of health problems at suburb level or above, but by drilling it down to a smaller, neighbourhood level you begin to see a very different story,&quot; Dr Hanigan said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said that, for example, it is globally well known that socio-economic disadvantage is associated with more heart disease problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Being able to peer down to street-level maps of disadvantage can reveal these pockets of very high risk, right in the middle of some of our more affluent suburbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Health data administrators are restricted by certain interpretations of the privacy laws and this has unintentionally led to the suppression of data access by researchers. Our ability to make adequate disease maps and do correlation analysis is then hampered,” Dr Hanigan said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A lot of money is being spent on data collection and this needs to be better used to improve public health, especially risk identification and prevention. There is a trade-off between the public health benefits of geographical research on health versus the protection of individual privacy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study examined low scale statistical areas and compared them with larger scale areas to uncover the differences in risk factors and health problems. Dr Hanigan said they found that rates of heart attack hospitalisation had distinct peaks and troughs across most suburbs when using low scale analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When we examined the same areas at larger scale, we found those peaks and troughs largely disappeared becoming far smoother across these suburbs. In some cases, these suburb-level results were four times lower than the rates seen in low scale analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s clear that the scale of analysis can change the understanding of geographical patterns of risk factors and diseases. This needs to be taken into account in planning future health data analysis, and when health authorities and the government review the evidence and work on population health policies,” Dr Hanigan said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report is co-authored by University of Canbera Professor of Public Health Tom Cochrane and HRI Director Professor Rachel Davey.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2017-11-29 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2017/11/the-impact-of-scale/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>New paper on neighbourhood level air pollution for health research</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;This post is to announce an recent paper we got published:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blending multiple nitrogen dioxide data sources for neighborhood estimates of long-term exposure for health research. Ivan Charles Hanigan, Grant J Williamson, Luke David Knibbs, Joshua Horsley, Margaret Rolfe, Martin Cope, Adrian Barnett, Christine Cowie, Jane S Heyworth, Marc L Serre, Bin Jalaludin, Geoffrey G Morgan. 2017, Environmental Science &amp;amp; Technology, &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.7b03035&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.7b03035&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exposure to nitrogen dioxide (NO2) pollution has been associated with a range of adverse health outcomes for both the respiratory and cardiovascular systems. This pollutant is primarily emitted by traffic and can reach very high levels next to roads, and diminish quickly away from the source. Spatial models of pollution concentrations are often used to estimate exposure levels that are then fed into models that estimate health impacts. However, these estimates can be imprecise due to difficulty modelling spatial patterns at the resolution of neighbourhoods (e.g. a scale of tens of metres) rather than at a coarse scale (around several kilometres). This is especially challenging at low concentrations, such as the level found in Sydney Australia.  The Sydney region has globally low levels of air pollution compared with similar economically developed cities. Rome for example is a similar size yet mean NO2 was three times higher than the average in Sydney.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objective of our research was to derive improved estimates of neighbourhood level pollutant concentrations for health studies by blending air pollutant measurements with modelled predictions using the Bayesian statistical philosophy. The improved estimates of exposure will theoretically reduce bias when used in second stage analyses of the impacts on health. This improved evidence will guide decision makers in the delicate balance between the costs of reducing air pollution emissions, while minimising health impacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our paper that has just been accepted for publication in the journal Environmental Science &amp;amp; Technology we implemented a high-tech method called the Bayesian Maximum Entropy (BME) model to blend data based on our prior knowledge of the probabilities and uncertainty surrounding the information sources. We brought together all the different NO2 data from measuring stations (monitors), chemical transport models (physical models that mimic the dispersion of emissions and weather patterns), and statistical ‘land use regression’ models (which incorporated satellite-based data) to estimate neighbourhood level annual average NO2 concentrations in Sydney. Our validation assessment using independent data from a separate set of samples showed an improvement compared to either the land use regression and chemical transport model used alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How low should we go? Is there a ‘safe’ low threshold of air pollution for Australians?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Future outputs of our work will seek to enable the policy and management communities to develop further improvements to air pollution maps and to explore health cost-benefit estimates under various emission reduction scenarios. For example, the Australian National Environment Protection Council decides on the National Environment Protection Measures (NEPMs) which have the goal of achieving a safe threshold of exposure in our cities. The results of our research will inform these stakeholders as they revise the regulations, and try to achieve the National Clean Air Agreement (made between the Commonwealth and each state and territory jurisdictions) which aims to implement strengthened laws that move to even tighter standards on air pollution emissions by 2025.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Key talking points:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Air pollution health impacts are well known from studies in high concentration cities (e.g. Rome) but there is a lack of knowledge about how low we need to go to minimise health impacts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sydney has globally low levels of NO2 (a traffic related air pollutant) and this makes Australia one of the best places in the world to study this low end of the exposure spectrum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our study produced an air pollution map with the best validation statistics for NO2 made so far for Sydney, at a scale of hundreds of metres.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These more precise exposure estimates will produce better knowledge about the health impacts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With this evidence we can make better choices on regulatory interventions that seek to maximise the health benefits of reducing air pollution emissions while also delivering the lifestyle and economic prosperity afforded by burning fossil fuel for energy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Media release&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;A breath of fresh air – new pollution research from Australia&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calculating whether traffic-related air pollution exposure can make us sick even at low levels has stumped experts around the world, but new research from a collaboration among eight universities and the CSIRO is now filling in the blanks.
Nitrogen dioxide (NO2) is a pollutant mostly emitted by traffic and has been associated with respiratory and cardiovascular health problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research, Blending Multiple Nitrogen Dioxide Data Sources for Neighborhood
Estimates of Long-Term Exposure for Health Research has been published in the journal Environmental Science and Technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lead author Dr Ivan Hanigan from the University of Canberra’s Health Research Institute and the Centre for air quality and health Research and evaluation (CAR) based at University of Sydney says past studies of NO2 pollution have focused on major cities around the world, mostly with severe problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We know about the health impacts because of research which examined cities like Rome, which have very high concentrations of pollution,” Dr Hanigan said. “While, Sydney is about the same size as Rome; the Italian capital has three times higher levels of NO­2 pollution. It is still a big unknown if there might be a safe lower threshold where health impacts are minimal.  If there is, then emission reduction policies can use this as a target, but if not then continual pollution reduction measures may be justified. Sydney is therefore one of the best places in the world to study this, and we can help answer this globally significant question.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Using the very precise air quality monitors installed around Sydney, along with sophisticated modelling by my collaborators, we are gaining insights that other studies have missed about the lower levels of NO2 exposure. We’ve been able to produce the best maps so far of air pollution for Sydney, and the scale is down to a hundred metres or so.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous analysis used scales of several kilometres, Dr Hanigan says his new maps are much closer to the level of detail needed to accurately determine health impacts and plan for the future.
“I expect health policy experts, infrastructure planners and even environmental managers will be keenly interested in this analysis,” he said. “This work can help to develop improvements to Australia’s air pollution regulations and lead to better health cost-benefit estimates for emission reduction scenarios.”
“With this evidence we can make better choices on interventions to maximise the health benefits of reducing air pollution emissions while also delivering the lifestyle and economic prosperity afforded by burning fossil fuels for energy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work is a collaboration between Dr Hanigan and colleagues from around Australia and the United States, including from University of Tasmania, University of Queensland, University of Sydney, CSIRO, Queensland University of Technology, University of New South Wales, University of Western Australia and the University of North Carolina.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2017-11-16 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2017/11/new-paper-on-neighbourhood-level-air-pollution-for-health-research/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Reproducible ecosystem risk assessment as virtual desktop case study</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper on a computational environment for reproducible workflows for climate change assessments is available for free access for limited time until Jan 28 via &lt;a href=&quot;https://authors.elsevier.com/a/1UBJF5c6cKey5~&quot;&gt;https://authors.elsevier.com/a/1UBJF5c6cKey5~&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guru, S., Hanigan, I. C., Nguyen, H. A., Burns, E., Stein, J., Blanchard, W., Lindenmayer, D., Clancy, T. (2016). Development of a cloud-based platform for reproducible science: A case study of an IUCN Red List of Ecosystems Assessment. Ecological Informatics, 36, 221–230. &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoinf.2016.08.003&quot;&gt;http://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoinf.2016.08.003&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this project we re-implemented a previously created project from an ArcGIS and R scripted process into a reproducible workflow in Kepler. That original analysis was for a climate change risk assessment using the IUCN Red list of Ecosystems Assessment framework and was done for Mountain Ash forests located in the Central Highlands of Victoria, Australia.  This served as our case study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our aim was to demonstrate how this could be implemented as a more reproducible workflow and how it could be disseminated by creating a standalone computation environment for sharing the entire operating system and toolchain along with the work. The IT infrastructure we developed offers analysis tools as a “Platform as a Service” in a virtual desktop offered as a “Desktop as a Service” at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coesra.org.au&quot;&gt;https://www.coesra.org.au&lt;/a&gt; and new features are under development at &lt;a href=&quot;https://portal.coesra.org.au&quot;&gt;https://portal.coesra.org.au&lt;/a&gt;.  A R package of generic functions was created &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/coesra/iucnecosystemriskassessment/src&quot;&gt;https://bitbucket.org/coesra/iucnecosystemriskassessment/src&lt;/a&gt;, and execution is possible as a pipeline of R scripts &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/coesra/iucn_ecosystemriskassessment_mountainashforests&quot;&gt;https://bitbucket.org/coesra/iucn_ecosystemriskassessment_mountainashforests&lt;/a&gt; as well as a Kepler workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made heavy use of the flowchart R function 'newnode' which I wrote as part of my
PhD project (and is distributed in my own misc R package available
on Github &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ivanhanigan/disentangle&quot;&gt;https://github.com/ivanhanigan/disentangle&lt;/a&gt;. This function takes a simple data.frame of steps, inputs and outputs and returns a string of text
written in the dot language which can be rendered in R using
the DiagrammeR package, or the standalone graphviz
package. This creates the graph view shown below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;object data=&quot;/images/iucn-criteria-Conceptual_workflow-v1-3-1.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf&quot; width=&quot;675&quot; height=&quot;800&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Alternative text - include a link &lt;a href=&quot;images/iucn-criteria-Conceptual_workflow-v1-3-1.pdf&quot;&gt;to the PDF!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;

</description>
				<published>2017-01-03 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2017/01/reproducible-ecosystem-risk-assessment-as-virtual-desktop-case-study/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>One Health Ecohealth Conference Melbourne Dec 2016</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I've just come out of an amazing 5 day conference on One Health (where animal health science meets human health science, and a whole lot of ecological thinking).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was truly terrifying to hear about the cascading risks to health from environmental change.  I was deeply affected by the story of monitoring worm infestation rates in children working in mines in the DRCongo, and saddened by the mass death of coral this year on the barrier reef (among many other tragic stories).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was good news too:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pepper and cinnamon fed to broiler chickens in India has been found to have antimicrobial properties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bhutan have made progress with rabies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yanks working with Ozzies are making progress on Hendra antibodies/vaccine for horses and humans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I met some very inspiring early career researchers and students&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I met some equally inspiring senior scientists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My drought index/Government Drought Declarations poster was viewed by the former head of the Gov. Department who was in charge of the drought declarations (we agreed that the underlying governmental decision rules are vague and multipurpose, and a climate index has great value when looking at human ecology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I also gathered some AVA CPD points (whatever they are!) as alerted by this certificate they sent me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ecohealth_cert.png&quot; alt=&quot;/images/ecohealth_cert.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2016-12-08 00:00:00 +1100</published>
				<link>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2016/12/one-health-ecohealth-conference-melbourne-dec-2016/</link>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>