<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>Recology</title>
		<description>An exploration of using R for ecology, evolution, and open science.</description>
		<link>http://schamberlain.github.com</link>
		
			<item>
				<title>graphviz-automagic-flowcharts</title>
				<description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Back in 2009 Joseph Guillaume worked with me on a complicated workflow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He came up with this python script to help keep track of the steps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The simple text file is a list of transformations, inputs and output&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is converted to the right format and graphviz creates a html page with pop-outs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Simple text list&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Transformation
        description
                the thing 
        inputs
                the thing before
                another thing
        output
                the next thing
        notes
                the thing is this other thing   this is a really long description 
                blah blah asdfasdfasdfasdfasdfa 

Transformation
        description
                yet another thing
        inputs
                the next thing
        output
                a final thing
        notes
                this is a note
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keep this in your work directory and update it whenever you add a step to the workflow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the list can be as big as you like (hundreds of steps), and entered in any order, the inputs/output relationships determine how the graph looks at the end&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to run the script just do the one line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Python code: run&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;python transformations.py workflow_steps.txt index
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;open the html page and click on a square box to bring up the pop-out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;short text is shown, long text is replaced by an ellipse and only shown in pop-out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've popped the script up as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ivanhanigan/transformations&quot;&gt;Github repo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The example is in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ivanhanigan.github.io/transformations/&quot;&gt;gh-pages branch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<published>Sun Dec 01 00:00:00 +1100 2013</published>
				<link>http://schamberlain.github.com/2013/12/graphviz-automagic-flowcharts/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>sharing-and-extending-research-protocols</title>
				<description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Last week I started a new discussion about sharing and extending research protocols.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;My Colleague sent me a link to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://prometheuswiki.publish.csiro.au/tiki-custom_home.php&quot;&gt;Prometheus Wiki&lt;/a&gt;​&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;a site for sharing research protocols. The idea is to give people
a place to post research protocols since everyone develops them
and then mentions them in papers but they rarely make it online in
a usable format. We see this as a big bottleneck in the rate of
knowledge discovery. Since users will always want to change and
adapt a given protocol for changing applications or new technology
or just to improve it. This sort of thing is done with open source
all the time (i.e. git) but how you'd do it with an online
protocol based out of a wiki is unknown. The current version of
the website is not very flexible and doesn't really enable the
sort of dynamic collaboration that I envision would make this a
really useful tool. Git seems like an obvious conceptual starting
point but there'd need to be a front end markup system in place
that was integrated with that git-type backend. Since you've
mentioned git a few times and the open science project, I thought
you might find this interesting to think about. any suggestions or
inspirations would be welcomed
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;My past experience&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have previously tried to use a wiki for the development of new sections in an existing study protocol on estimating the effects of bushfire smoke air pollution and human health.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We combined elements of two major air pollution/health study protocols (one from Europe, one from America) with local considerations and decisions made within our team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On reflection all this was mostly useful for me, to a lesser extent the other programmer and I don't think the project manager or statistician ever even looked at any of this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Jeff Leek's current approach using GitHub&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been keeping an eye on the work by Jeff Leek on putting protocols onto Github and inviting collaboration to edit and extend them &lt;a href=&quot;http://simplystatistics.org/2013/10/07/the-leek-group-policy-for-developing-sustainable-r-packages/&quot;&gt;as he says&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;I put it on Github because I'm still not 100% sure I got it
right... I would welcome feedback/pull requests on how we can
improve the policy to make it better
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Leek Group policies and protocols on github so far&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jtleek/rpackages&quot;&gt;https://github.com/jtleek/rpackages&lt;/a&gt; accompanied by &lt;a href=&quot;http://simplystatistics.org/2013/10/07/the-leek-group-policy-for-developing-sustainable-r-packages/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jtleek/reviews&quot;&gt;https://github.com/jtleek/reviews&lt;/a&gt; accompanied by &lt;a href=&quot;http://simplystatistics.org/2013/10/23/the-leek-group-guide-to-reviewing-scientific-papers/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jtleek/datasharing&quot;&gt;https://github.com/jtleek/datasharing&lt;/a&gt; accompanied by &lt;a href=&quot;http://simplystatistics.org/2013/11/14/the-leek-group-guide-to-sharing-data-with-a-statistician-to-speed-collaboration/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;I forked &quot;datasharing&quot; for my own. Renamed: &quot;How to share data to avoid misunderstanding&quot;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I liked the datasharing policy so much &lt;a href=&quot;http://ivanhanigan.github.io/datasharing/&quot;&gt;I forked it for my own collaborations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I initially just made a minor recommendation to one of the lines in the original using the great Github feature that if you edit a repo you don't have access to, it forks the repo and creates a feature branch behind the scenes. After you submit the changes (which is a commit) it puts you right into the pull request form.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore it can all be done on the GitHub site. I submitted &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jtleek/datasharing/pull/11&quot;&gt;the pull request without leaving my web browser&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But then I thought I would have done things a bit differently.  In particular I'd like a webpage with a table of contents, and a nicer looking landing page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;so I cloned my fork of the repo, then created a new branch called gh-pages, then copied the original to a new file called index.org, added some Emacs Orgmode HTML export magic and then &quot;C-c C-e h&quot; and WHAMM-O I've got my own version for extending with at &lt;a href=&quot;http://ivanhanigan.github.io/datasharing/&quot;&gt;http://ivanhanigan.github.io/datasharing/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;The code version:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git clone git@github.com:ivanhanigan/datasharing.git ~/tools/datasharing
cd ~/tools/datasharing
git branch gh-pages
mv README.md index.org
touch README.md
# edits to index.org, &quot;C-c C-e h&quot; and WHAMM-O
git add index.org index.html README.md
git push origin gh-pages
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In this way I think people can share and collaborate easily &lt;a href=&quot;http://yihui.name/en/2013/06/fix-typo-in-documentation/&quot;&gt;(if they know git)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as well as easily take work started by someone else and extend it for their own work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wonder a little bit about how much of my extensions I should offer back to Jeff Leek as the original author.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I guess he can always track what I do to it via the link back to his original shown in &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jtleek/datasharing/network&quot;&gt;https://github.com/jtleek/datasharing/network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;PS Jeff Leek uses github a lot!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As he says in &lt;a href=&quot;http://simplystatistics.org/2013/11/21/future-of-statistics-take-home-messages-futureofstats/&quot;&gt;this post from the future-of-statistics unconference&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;You can read it on Github here (https://github.com/jtleek/futureofstats).
I put it on Github for two reasons:

- I agree with Hadley's statement that the future of statistics is on Github.
- I summarized them based on my interpretation and would love
  collaboration on the document. If you want to add your new
  thoughts/summaries, add a new section with your bullet pointed
  ideas and send me a pull request!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jeff Leek is on to something really interesting with these github policies and protocols&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I find the look of his plain markdown README.md pages a bit un-inspiring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but then I spend too much of my time tweaking my html by far (while Jeff is getting on with the real work of publishing papers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<published>Wed Nov 27 00:00:00 +1100 2013</published>
				<link>http://schamberlain.github.com/2013/11/sharing-and-extending-research-protocols/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>our-paper-is-out-heat-health-warning-systems</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Finally our article has been published in final version in Environmental Health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Title: The impact of heat on mortality and morbidity in the Greater Metropolitan Sydney Region: a case crossover analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Authors: Wilson Ann Leigh, Gerard Morgan  Geoffrey, Hanigan Charles Ivan, Johnston H Fay, Abu-Rayya  Hisham, Broome  Richard, Gaskin  Clive, Jalaludin  Bin,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Environmental Health.2013, 12:98.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DOI: 10.1186/10.1186/1476-069X-12-98&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;URL: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ehjournal.net/content/12/1/98&quot;&gt;http://www.ehjournal.net/content/12/1/98&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally.......
thanks to everyone,  especially Geoff Morgan, Richard Broome, Fay Johnston; Bin Jalaludin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And especially Leigh Wilson.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>Wed Nov 27 00:00:00 +1100 2013</published>
				<link>http://schamberlain.github.com/2013/11/our-paper-is-out-heat-health-warning-systems/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>guest-post-by-marco-fahmi-why-morpho</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I asked my colleague &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/fahmiger&quot;&gt;Marco Fahmi&lt;/a&gt; to
post this as a guest post.  It came my way as a part of an email
exchange in which another colleague had a question regarding their task
of recording previous work in an ecological field study:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ideally in such a way that we would end up with a complete metadata
profile of previous work carried out. I would also like to see the
establishment of a system that could also be used by the group going
forward to keep track of information and data produced at the
site. I hear you have been involved with establishing the
a metadata reporting system. How does this effort currently stand,
is it online? I was also wondering if you would be amenable to sharing
what you have with us with the hope that i could use this as a model
for our own system.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Our colleague Sheila responded first that:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All metadata are created using a standard template document and then transfered into a software package called &lt;a href=&quot;http://knb.ecoinformatics.org/morphoportal.jsp&quot;&gt;Morpho&lt;/a&gt;.  Metadata are then uploaded with the data to the Australian Supersite Network (ASN) Portal &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tern-supersites.net.au/knb/&quot;&gt;http://www.tern-supersites.net.au/knb/&lt;/a&gt;.   Any other useful documents are uploaded to the website &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tern-supersites.net.au&quot;&gt;http://www.tern-supersites.net.au&lt;/a&gt; either under the specific supersite tab on the left hand menu or under the Publications - Resources for SuperSite Users tab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Marco says:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morpho is an open source piece of software designed to host all kinds of ecological data. More information about how we use it at ASN can be found here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tern-supersites.net.au/index.php/data/repository-tutorial&quot;&gt;http://www.tern-supersites.net.au/index.php/data/repository-tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morpho should be enough for an individual researcher to organise and describe their personal data collection. If you want to share the data with colleagues or publish them online, then you will also need Metacat. There is a worldwide Metacat server available from the link account. All you need to do is request an account and connect to it via Morpho. Alternatively you can set up your own; but then you will need your own server and tech knowhow to configure it (and maintain it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For technical reasons, we have our own server running an older version of the Metacat software. You are welcome to use it if you wish (Shiela can issue you an account to log in and upload). We are also happy to provide assistance if you want to set something a standalone server for DRO. (Like any other piece of infrastructure, someone will need to look after the server after it is set up, so that's probably a decision that will need to be considered carefully).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;My comment:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&quot;Morpho should be enough for an individual researcher to organise
and describe their personal data collection&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree, but would emphasise the &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; and then say &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; ...
Ultimately I'd like to see something as easy and intuitive as iTunes for music or Endnote and Mendeley for bibliographies, but...&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>Wed Nov 27 00:00:00 +1100 2013</published>
				<link>http://schamberlain.github.com/2013/11/guest-post-by-marco-fahmi-why-morpho/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>a-sharp-looking-orgmode-latex-export-header</title>
				<description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I got this header for a nice looking report from Bull, G. (2011). Example Sweave Document. SharpStatistics.co.uk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This has a bunch of useful parameters, but I just really like the header and footer on pages 2 onward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The original was a Sweave file.  I really like Sweave but orgmode allows other languages as well as R to be inter-woven into the script&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An alternative to Sweave is knitr and is still on my todo list, but this works well at the moment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also like how you can quickly change this to a Beamer presentation style.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once this is in your file use C-c C-e d to export and compile the PDF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This example is available at &lt;a href=&quot;/pdfs/SharpReportTemplate.pdf&quot;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Emacs orgmode Code: Put this into your .org file&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#+TITLE: Sharp Report Template
#+AUTHOR: Ivan Hanigan
#+email: ivan.hanigan@anu.edu.au
#+LaTeX_CLASS: article
#+LaTeX_CLASS_OPTIONS: [a4paper]
#+LaTeX_HEADER: \usepackage{amssymb,amsmath}
#+LaTeX_HEADER: \usepackage{fancyhdr} %For headers and footers
#+LaTeX_HEADER: \pagestyle{fancy} %For headers and footers
#+LaTeX_HEADER: \usepackage{lastpage} %For getting page x of y
#+LaTeX_HEADER: \usepackage{float} %Allows the figures to be positioned and formatted nicely
#+LaTeX_HEADER: \floatstyle{boxed} %using this
#+LaTeX_HEADER: \restylefloat{figure} %and this command
#+LaTeX_HEADER: \usepackage{url} %Formatting of yrls
#+LaTeX_HEADER: \lhead{ivanhanigan.github.com}
#+LaTeX_HEADER: \chead{}
#+LaTeX_HEADER: \rhead{\today}
#+LaTeX_HEADER: \lfoot{Draft}
#+LaTeX_HEADER: \cfoot{}
#+LaTeX_HEADER: \rfoot{\thepage\ of \pageref{LastPage}}
#+LATEX: \tableofcontents

* Introduction
This is a sharp looking report template I got from an R blogger \cite{Bull2011}.

The pages after the first page have a nice looking header, footer and page number.
\clearpage

* Section 1
In the Org file you can see some hidden R code that computes a linear regression and returns the results shown in Table \ref{ATable}.
\input{ATable.tex}
\clearpage
*** COMMENT some-code
#+name:some-code
#+begin_src R :session *R* :tangle no :exports none :eval yes
#### name:some-code ####
x&amp;lt;-rnorm(100,10,5)
y&amp;lt;-rnorm(100,20,15)
fit &amp;lt;- lm(y~x)
library(xtable)
sink(&quot;ATable.tex&quot;)
xtable(fit, caption=&quot;Example Table&quot;,digits=4,table.placement=&quot;H&quot;,label=&quot;ATable&quot;)
sink()
#+end_src

#+RESULTS: some-code



* References
\bibliographystyle{apalike}
\bibliography{/home/ivan_hanigan/references/library}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
				<published>Tue Nov 26 00:00:00 +1100 2013</published>
				<link>http://schamberlain.github.com/2013/11/a-sharp-looking-orgmode-latex-export-header/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Setting Up A Workflow Script With Code Chunks</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;This post describes some ideas and techniques I use to set up a &quot;workflow script&quot;.  I use this term to refer to the structured combination of code, data and narrative that make an executable Reproducible Research Report (RRR).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of these ideas are inpsired by  a great paper by Kieran Healy called  &quot;Choosing Your Workflow Applications&quot; available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kjhealy/workflow-paper&quot;&gt;https://github.com/kjhealy/workflow-paper&lt;/a&gt; to accompany &lt;a href=&quot;http://kieranhealyo.org/resources/emacs-starter-kit.html&quot;&gt;his Emacs Starter Kit&lt;/a&gt;. My shortened version of his main points are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 use a good code editor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 analyse data with scripts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 store your work simply and document it properly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 use a version control system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 Automate back ups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6 Avoid distracting gadgets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Here's my current approach in each of these categories&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 use Emacs with Orgmode (and kjhealy's drop-in set of useful defaults)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 Scripts that utilise the literate programming technique of mixing Code Chunks in with descriptive prose&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 John Myles White's ProjectTemplate R Package and Josh Riech's LCFD paradigm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 git and GitHub for version control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;5 Automated Backups and 6 Avoiding Gadgets are still somethings I find challenging&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;1 Use a good code editor&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like using Emacs with Orgmode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have previously tried a variety of code editors from Tinn-r, NppToR, Rstudio and Eclipse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emacs with Orgmode suits me the most because it has a great number of features especially the linkage with LaTeX or HTML export&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A key reference to look at for reasons why Emacs is so good for scientific work is Eric Schulte et al &lt;a href=&quot;www.jstatsoft.org/v46/i03%E2%80%8E&quot;&gt;&quot;A Multi-Language Computing Environment for Literate Programming&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Here is a &lt;a href=&quot;http://doc.norang.ca/org-mode.html&quot;&gt;link to a great orgmode description&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(this guy spends a lot of time on tweaking his set up)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;2 Analyse data with Scripts (stitch together code chunks)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use Scripts but prefer to think of them as stitched together Code Chunks with prose into Compendia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compendia are documents that weave together Code and Prose into an executable report&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The underlying philosophy is called Reproducible Research Reports&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A very useful tool is a keyboard shortcut to quickly create a chunk for code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;so you can be writing parts of the report like this: &quot;Blah Blah Blah as shown in Figure X and Table Y&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;then just hit the correct keys and WHAMM-O there is a new chunk ready for the code that creates Figure X and Table Y to be written.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Here is how I use Emacs to achieve this (the other editors I mentioned above also have the abiltiy to do this too).  The IPython Notebook does this stuff too but calls chunks &quot;cells&quot; for some reason.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Emacs Code: Put this into the ~/.emacs.d/init.el file&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(define-skeleton chunk-skeleton
  &quot;Info for a code chunk.&quot;
  &quot;Title: &quot;
  &quot;*** &quot; str &quot;-code\n&quot;
  &quot;#+name:&quot; str &quot;\n&quot;
  &quot;#+begin_src R :session *R* :tangle src/&quot; str &quot;.r :exports reports :eval no\n&quot;
  &quot;#### name:&quot; str &quot; ####\n&quot;
  &quot;\n&quot;
  &quot;#+end_src\n&quot;
)
(global-set-key [?\C-x ?\C-\\] 'chunk-skeleton)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Using the Emacs Shortcut&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;now whenever you type Control-x control-\ a new code chunk will appear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you'll be typing &quot;blah blah blah&quot; and think I need a figure or table, just hit it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;move into the empty section and add some code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you can hit C-c ' to enter a org-babel code execution session that will be able to send these line by line to an R session&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;or within the main org buffer if your eval flag is set to yes then you can run the entire chunk (and return tabular output to the doc) using C-c C-c&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To export the code chunks and create the modular code scripts without the narrative prose use C-c C-v t&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this is called &quot;tangling&quot; and the chunks will be written out to the file specified in the chunk header &quot;:tangle&quot; flag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Compiling the resulting Compendium&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emacs uses LaTeX or HTML to produce the Report&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I find both of these outputs very pleasing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to compile to TEX use C-c C-e d&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for HTML use C-c C-e h (FOR CODE HIGHLIGHTING INSTALL htmlize.el)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;these commands will also evaluate all the chunks where &quot;:eval&quot; = yes to load the data and calculate the results fresh.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AWESOME!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;3 Store your work simply and document it properly&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I use the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.johnmyleswhite.com/notebook/2010/08/26/projecttemplate/&quot;&gt;ProjectTemplate R package&lt;/a&gt; to organise my code sections into modules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These modules are organised into the Reichian LCFD paradigm described first &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/a/1434424&quot;&gt;on StackOverflow here&lt;/a&gt;, and encoded into &lt;a href=&quot;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/makeProject/makeProject.pdf&quot;&gt;the makeProject R package&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;documentation is within the main orgmode script&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;data documentation is a whole other universe that I will deal with in a separate post&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;4 use a version control system using git and github&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# once you have the project via R
R
require(ProjectTemplate)
create.project(&quot;AwesomeProject&quot;, minimal = T)
q()
# use the shell to start a git repo
cd AwesomeProject
git init
# and commit the TODO
git add TODO
git commit -m &quot;first commit&quot;
# tada!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emacs can now be used to manage the git repo using the C-x g command&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rstudio has a really nice GUI for doing this inside it;s Project management interface too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Using Github or another Git Server&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can easily set up a Github repo for this now but it will be public&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alternatative is to set up your own private Git server.  I followed &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.goosoftware.co.uk/2012/02/07/quick-git-server/&quot;&gt;these instructions to Running a Simple Git Server Using SSH&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Either way once you have set up your remote git repo you need to set the remote tracking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Git Code:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd /path/to/local/git/repo
git remote add origin git@github-or-other-server:myname/myproject.git
git push origin master
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;5 Automate back ups AND 6 Avoid distracting gadgets&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OMG backups stress me out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ideally I would follow &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jwz.org/blog/2007/09/psa-backups/&quot;&gt;this advice because &quot;when it comes to losing your data the universe tends toward maximum irony. Don't push it.&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But I don;t fully comply&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instead I generally use Dropbox for  basic project management admin stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I use github for code projects I am happy to share, I also pay for 10 private repos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I Set up a git server at my workplace for extra projects but this is on a test server that is not backed up, and I am not really happy about this&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In terms of Distracting Gadgets, I think that with the current tempo of new innovations related to new software tools for this type of work I should keep trying new things but I have pretty much settled into a comfortable zone with the gadgets I described here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is how I've worked for a couple of years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I find it very enjoyable, mostly productive but prone to the distractions of &quot;distractions by gadgets&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The main thing I want to point out is the usage of Code Chunks in RRR scripts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These things are awesome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<published>Mon Nov 25 00:00:00 +1100 2013</published>
				<link>http://schamberlain.github.com/2013/11/setting-up-a-workflow-with-code-chunks/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>sync-endnote-and-mendeley-references-using-r-xml</title>
				<description>&lt;h4&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I use Mendeley (despite them being bought out by Elsevier, who used to sell guns)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My Colleagues use EndNote&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need to sync, they find Endnote better for their workflow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I tried to export my Mendeley as XML and import to Endnote, but found many duplicates that took time to rectify&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(and the risk is there that the RefNo they used in the Doc will be the duplicate that I removed)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Aims&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;test if R and the XML package can help find refs in Endnote that aren't in Mendeley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If so can I write those into an Mendeley import for seamless integrations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and what about going from Mendeley to Endnote?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Methods&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The R XML package seems an obvious place to start&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;before writing a function, just step thru the process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Step 1: export XML from Mendeley and Endnote&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Mendeley Just select the refs in the list and then from the file menu&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Endnote it is also under File menu&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Step 2: R Code:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# func
# might need sudo apt-get install r-cran-xml?
require(XML)

# load
dir()
[1] &quot;EndnoteCollection.xml&quot;
    &quot;MendeleyCollection.Data&quot;
[3] &quot;MendeleyCollection.xml&quot; 

d1 &amp;lt;- xmlTreeParse(&quot;EndnoteCollection.xml&quot;, useInternal=T)

# clean
str(d1)
# ooooh xml schmexemhel voodoo?

# do
top &amp;lt;- xmlRoot(d1)
str(top)
names(top)
# top [[1]] # prints the whole thing
top [[1]][[1]]
top [[1]][[2]]
# prints a record (1 or 2)

# just messing around
length(top[[1]])
top [[1]][[120]]
names(top [[1]][[120]])
names(top [[1]][[120]][[&quot;contributors&quot;]])
names(top [[1]][[120]][[&quot;contributors&quot;]][[&quot;authors&quot;]])
top [[1]][[120]][[&quot;contributors&quot;]][[&quot;authors&quot;]][[2]]

i &amp;lt;- 110
top [[1]][[i]]
as.matrix(names(top [[1]][[i]]))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;OK so XML as a list.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I think if I do a merge of two author-date-title dataframes I can easily find the diffs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;TRY a square wheel&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;R Code:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;endnote_mendeley_df &amp;lt;- function(input_xml,
                                nrow_to_try = 1000){
  d1 &amp;lt;- xmlTreeParse(input_xml, useInternal=T)
  top &amp;lt;- xmlRoot(d1)

  output &amp;lt;- matrix(ncol = 4, nrow = 0)
  for(i in 1:nrow_to_try)
  {
  # i = 1000
    if(is.na(xmlValue(top [[1]][[i]]))) break
    if(
      !is.na(xmlValue(top [[1]][[i]][[&quot;contributors&quot;]][[&quot;authors&quot;]][[2]]))
      )
    {
      author &amp;lt;- paste(xmlValue(top [[1]][[i]][[&quot;contributors&quot;]][[&quot;authors&quot;]][[1]]), &quot;et al&quot;, &quot; &quot;)
    } else {
      author &amp;lt;- xmlValue(top [[1]][[i]][[&quot;contributors&quot;]][[&quot;authors&quot;]][[1]])
    }
    year &amp;lt;- xmlValue(top [[1]][[i]][[&quot;dates&quot;]][[&quot;year&quot;]])
    title &amp;lt;- xmlValue(top [[1]][[i]][[&quot;titles&quot;]][[1]])
    endnoteref &amp;lt;- xmlValue(top [[1]][[i]][[&quot;rec-number&quot;]])
    output &amp;lt;- rbind(output, c(author, year, title, endnoteref))

  }
  output &amp;lt;- as.data.frame(output)
  return(output)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;R Test:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;output &amp;lt;- endnote_mendeley_df(
  input_xml = &quot;EndnoteCollection.xml&quot;
  ,
  nrow_to_try = 10
  )

nrow(output)
write.csv(output, &quot;EndnoteCollection.csv&quot;, row.names = F)
output  &amp;lt;- read.csv(&quot;EndnoteCollection.csv&quot;, stringsAsFactors = F)
str(output)
output[,1:2]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;R Do-read:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;endnote &amp;lt;- endnote_mendeley_df(
  input_xml = &quot;EndnoteCollection.xml&quot;
  )
nrow(endnote)
mendeley &amp;lt;- endnote_mendeley_df(
  input_xml = &quot;MendeleyCollection.xml&quot;
  )
nrow(mendeley)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;R Do-concatenate and lowercase&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# TODO this is a really terrible way to do this.
# FIXME find out how to compare the two better
require(stringr)
mendeley2 &amp;lt;- str_c(mendeley$V1, mendeley$V2, mendeley$V3)
mendeley2 &amp;lt;- gsub(&quot; &quot;, &quot;&quot;, mendeley2)
mendeley2 &amp;lt;- gsub(&quot;,&quot;, &quot;&quot;, mendeley2)
mendeley2 &amp;lt;- tolower(mendeley2)
mendeley2[1:5]
mendeley$mendeley2 &amp;lt;- mendeley2

# now do this again from endnote
endnote2 &amp;lt;- str_c(endnote$V1, endnote$V2, endnote$V3)
endnote2 &amp;lt;- gsub(&quot; &quot;, &quot;&quot;, endnote2)
endnote2 &amp;lt;- gsub(&quot;,&quot;, &quot;&quot;, endnote2)
endnote2 &amp;lt;- tolower(endnote2)
endnote2[1:5]
endnote$endnote2 &amp;lt;- endnote2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;R Do-merge:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;endnote_not_in_mendeley &amp;lt;- merge(endnote,
                                 mendeley,
                                 by.x = &quot;endnote2&quot;,
                                 by.y = &quot;mendeley2&quot;,
                                 all.x = T)
str(endnote_not_in_mendeley)
nrow(endnote_not_in_mendeley)
head(endnote_not_in_mendeley)
endnote_not_in_mendeley &amp;lt;- endnote_not_in_mendeley[
                                                   is.na(endnote_not_in_mendeley$V1.y),
                                                   ]
nrow(endnote_not_in_mendeley)
# 66 refs in endnote are not in mendeley
write.csv(endnote_not_in_mendeley,
      &quot;endnote_not_in_mendeley.csv&quot;, row.names = F)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Open this as spreadsheet and cross check&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make a new column for comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;check off which ones were in AllDocuments and not in the Mendeley group&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this diff was because of when I imported the Endnote XML but had not assigned these to the mendeley group&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;once have cleaned up the mendeley group export again and then check which are in mendeley but not in endnote&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;First here is a note&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;about a way to speed up the checks, excluding false positives using fuzzy matching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my method relies on the author, date and title to be written the same in both ie initials then surname or visa verca&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But this is not always true&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I previously used levenshtein string matching to identify strings that are close but not identical&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.r-project.org/rwiki/doku.php?id=tips:data-strings:levenshtein&quot;&gt;Try this link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://rwiki.sciviews.org/doku.php?id=tips:data-strings:levenshtein&quot;&gt;OR this link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TODO I will share this code as a GitHub Gist later!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;R Code: possibility to speed up Checks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;tmp1 &amp;lt;- mendeley[grep(&quot;Walker&quot;, mendeley$V1),&quot;mendeley2&quot;]
tmp2 &amp;lt;- endnote[grep(&quot;Walker&quot;, endnote$V1),&quot;endnote2&quot;]

# these differ slightly
# B. Walker et al vs Walker, Brian et al
source(&quot;~/Dropbox/tools/levenshtein.r&quot;)
levenshtein(
    tmp1
    ,
    tmp2
    )
# gives 92percent match
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;R Code: Find mendeley refs without endnote&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  endnote &amp;lt;- endnote_mendeley_df(
    input_xml = &quot;EndnoteCollection.xml&quot;
    )
  nrow(endnote)
  mendeley &amp;lt;- endnote_mendeley_df(
    input_xml = &quot;MendeleyCollection2.xml&quot;
    )
  nrow(mendeley)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;R Code: Do-concatenate and lowercase&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;require(stringr)
mendeley2 &amp;lt;- str_c(mendeley$V1, mendeley$V2, mendeley$V3)
mendeley2 &amp;lt;- gsub(&quot; &quot;, &quot;&quot;, mendeley2)
mendeley2 &amp;lt;- gsub(&quot;,&quot;, &quot;&quot;, mendeley2)
mendeley2 &amp;lt;- tolower(mendeley2)
mendeley2[1:5]
mendeley$mendeley2 &amp;lt;- mendeley2

# now do this again from endnote
endnote2 &amp;lt;- str_c(endnote$V1, endnote$V2, endnote$V3)
endnote2 &amp;lt;- gsub(&quot; &quot;, &quot;&quot;, endnote2)
endnote2 &amp;lt;- gsub(&quot;,&quot;, &quot;&quot;, endnote2)
endnote2 &amp;lt;- tolower(endnote2)
endnote2[1:5]
endnote$endnote2 &amp;lt;- endnote2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;R Do-merge:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;mendeley_not_in_endnote &amp;lt;- merge(mendeley,
                                 endnote,
                                 by.y = &quot;endnote2&quot;,
                                 by.x = &quot;mendeley2&quot;,
                                 all.x = T)
str(mendeley_not_in_endnote)
nrow(mendeley_not_in_endnote)
head(mendeley_not_in_endnote)
mendeley_not_in_endnote &amp;lt;- mendeley_not_in_endnote[
                                                      is.na(mendeley_not_in_endnote$V1.y),
                                                      ]
nrow(mendeley_not_in_endnote)
# 92 refs in endnote are not in mendeley
write.csv(mendeley_not_in_endnote,
      &quot;mendeley_not_in_endnote.csv&quot;, row.names = F)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Not all these 92 will be true&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;so let;s try the string matching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;R Code:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;source(&quot;~/Dropbox/tools/levenshtein.r&quot;)
pcnt_threshold &amp;lt;- 0.6
out_list &amp;lt;- matrix(ncol = 3, nrow = 0)
#out_list &amp;lt;- read.csv(&quot;mendeley_not_in_endnote_fz_match.csv&quot;, stringsAsFactors = F)
for(i in 36:nrow(mendeley_not_in_endnote))
    {
        print(i)
#        i = 2
tmp1 &amp;lt;- mendeley_not_in_endnote[i,1]
    for(j in 1:nrow(endnote))
        {
    #        j = 2
    if(exists(&quot;out&quot;)) rm(out)
    tmp2 &amp;lt;- endnote$endnote2[j]
    pcnt &amp;lt;- levenshtein(
            tmp1
            ,
            tmp2
            )
    #pcnt
    if(pcnt &amp;gt;= pcnt_threshold) out &amp;lt;- tmp2
    if(exists(&quot;out&quot;))
        out_list &amp;lt;- rbind(out_list, c(tmp1, tmp2, pcnt))
    if(exists(&quot;out&quot;)) break
        }

    }
out_list
write.csv(out_list, &quot;mendeley_not_in_endnote_fz_match.csv&quot;, row.names = F)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;R Code: Do-concatenate and lowercase&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;require(stringr)
out_list &amp;lt;- read.csv(&quot;mendeley_not_in_endnote_fz_match.csv&quot;, stringsAsFactors = F)
mendeley2 &amp;lt;- read.csv(&quot;mendeley_not_in_endnote.csv&quot;, stringsAsFactors=F)
mendeley2[1,]
out_list[1,]
mendeley2 &amp;lt;- merge(mendeley_not_in_endnote, out_list,
                   by.x = &quot;mendeley2&quot;,
                   by.y = &quot;V1&quot;, all.x = T)
mendeley2[2,]
mendeley2 &amp;lt;- mendeley2[is.na(mendeley2$V3),]
nrow(mendeley2)
# 48 records
write.csv(mendeley2, &quot;mendeley_not_in_endnote_best_estimate.csv&quot;, row.names=F)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Results&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I found that XML package in R can work with the Endnote and Mendeley export Files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I think I made a lot of bad decisions about the way I went about  doing this!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It seemed quite difficult to get the XML stuff to make sense to me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I;ve heard that python has better libraries for working with XML&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the levenshtein string matching code proved useful again.  I should get out of the habit of looping and start using lapply etc to speed this up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was an interesting if frustrating experiment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The minor issues with importing from mendeley/endnote and deduplicating using their own tools was probably not worth writing all this half-baked R code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But I did learn more about working with XML in R (and realised this is probably not one of R's Strengths -- or mine for that matter!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<published>Wed Nov 20 00:00:00 +1100 2013</published>
				<link>http://schamberlain.github.com/2013/11/sync-endnote-and-mendeley-using-r-xml/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>git-can-be-simple-or-very-complicated</title>
				<description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Git is a Distributed Version Control System.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;centerforopenscience.org&quot;&gt;centerforopenscience.org&lt;/a&gt; has developed the Open Science Framework  which is they say &quot;a simplified front end to the powerful and popular version control system Git&quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I use Github a lot for extending the local features into an online space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So I finally got around to poking the open science framework with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://openscienceframework.org/project/pyts3/&quot;&gt;Hutchinson Drought Index project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It turns out to be too simplified, and not have very many of the feature I love about Git and GitHub :-(&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For eg it is not really distributed in that you don't get to sync your local repo with the onlin version&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you upload a script or dataset, then you continue editing locally until you want to commit and then you have to upload again, one file at a time with the GUI rather than &quot;git add .&quot; and &quot;git push&quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I recommend having a look, it might work for you, but if you want more power checkout Yihui's suggestions for using github &lt;a href=&quot;http://yihui.name/en/2011/12/how-to-become-an-efficient-and-collaborative-r-programmer/&quot;&gt;http://yihui.name/en/2011/12/how-to-become-an-efficient-and-collaborative-r-programmer/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and &lt;a href=&quot;http://yihui.name/en/2013/06/fix-typo-in-documentation/&quot;&gt;http://yihui.name/en/2013/06/fix-typo-in-documentation/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;In general I don't think simple front-end's should be a barrier to accessing a sophisticated back-end!&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
				<published>Tue Nov 19 00:00:00 +1100 2013</published>
				<link>http://schamberlain.github.com/2013/11/git-can-be-simple-or-very-complicated/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>nectar cloud pumilio build got bogged down</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I've been trying to build pumilio bioacoustics server on a Aust Nectar Research Cloud VM, but hit various roadblocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;built with NeCTAR Ubuntu 12.04.2 (Precise)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;these issues (especially the apt-get install r-cran-mysql etc ) might not occure with later Ubuntu?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;test NeCTAR Ubuntu 12.10 (Quantal) or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NeCTAR Ubuntu 13.04 (Raring) ??&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TODO FIX issues with python audio lab&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TODO swapfile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TODO Mount the larger storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TODO add swapfile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TODO fix R install etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The Github code (in the gh-pages branch) and published as &lt;a href=&quot;http://ivanhanigan.github.io/pumilio-bushfm/&quot;&gt;a report at this link&lt;/a&gt;.  The Source Code is available to Clone or Fork at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ivanhanigan/pumilio-bushfm&quot;&gt;This Github Repo&lt;/a&gt; and is at a stage that most of the installation and configuration is documented to a point where a test sound file has successfully been uploaded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;HELP WANTED&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any researcher at an Australia university could follow the instructions on their own Nectar Cloud VM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If anybody out there is interested in bioacoustics, R, Linux or web data archives please help&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Background to pumilio, bushfm and this project&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/birdcombined.png&quot; alt=&quot;birdcombined.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;pumilio%20project&quot;&gt;http://pumilio.sourceforge.net/&lt;/a&gt; is by Luis J. Villanueva-Rivera and Bryan C. Pijanowski. (2012. Pumilio: A Web-Based Management System for Ecological Recordings. Bulletin of the Ecological Society of America 93: 71-81. doi: 10.1890/0012-9623-93.1.71)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;Bush-fm%20project&quot;&gt;http://www.bush.fm/&lt;/a&gt; aims to provide the research community with a portal to national scale acoustic sensor data repositories, and a suite of tools to perform analysis and reporting on these data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Images from http://www.edwardtufte.com/bboard/q-and-a-fetch-msg?msg_id=0000M4)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>Mon Nov 18 00:00:00 +1100 2013</published>
				<link>http://schamberlain.github.com/2013/11/nectar-cloud-pumilio-build-got-bogged-down/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>really-useful-r-upcase-string</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Here is a really useful R snippet from  &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/a/6364905&quot;&gt;http://stackoverflow.com/a/6364905&lt;/a&gt; with a minor modification to allow differnt splits&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Code:r-upcase-string&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;x &amp;lt;- c(&quot;The&quot;, &quot;quick&quot;, &quot;Brown&quot;, &quot;fox/lazy dog&quot;)

simpleCap &amp;lt;- function(x, tosplit = &quot; &quot;) {
  s &amp;lt;- strsplit(x, tosplit)[[1]]
  paste(toupper(substring(s, 1,1)), substring(s, 2),
      sep=&quot;&quot;, collapse=tosplit)
}
sapply(x, simpleCap)
sapply(x, simpleCap, tosplit = &quot;/&quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
				<published>Sun Nov 17 00:00:00 +1100 2013</published>
				<link>http://schamberlain.github.com/2013/11/really-useful-r-upcase-string/</link>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>