<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>DisentangleThings</title>
 <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/feed/" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/"/>
 <updated>2016-05-10T23:23:48+10:00</updated>
 <id>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>ivanhanigan</name>
   <email>ivan.hanigan@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Judging the evidence part 2</title>
   <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2016/05/judging-the-evidence-part2/"/>
   <updated>2016-05-10T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2016/05/judging-the-evidence-part2</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I previously reported on a lecture slide deck called 'Judging the Evidence' by  Adrian Sleigh for a course PUBH7001 Introduction to Epidemiology, April 30, 2001.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/11/judging-the-evidence-using-a-literature-review-database&quot;&gt;http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/11/judging-the-evidence-using-a-literature-review-database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also now extracted several slides into a template outline for reviewing epidemiological and other research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Adrian Sleigh's Protocol&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Object of Study, Hypotheses or Research Questions&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Purpose of Study:  Objectives of study; why was it done?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reference Population:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To whom do authors generalize results?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To whom should the findings be generalized?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h5&gt;Sampling&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the Reference Pop (target population) -&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source Pop -&gt; Eligible population&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
The source population may be defined directly, as a matter of defining its membership criteria; or the definition may be indirect, as the catchment population of a defined way of identifying cases of the illness. The catchment population is, at any given time, the totality of those in the ‘were-would’ state of:  were the illness now to occur, it would be ‘caught’ by that case identification scheme Source: Miettinen OS, 2007 [http://www.teachepi.org/documents/courses/fundamentals/Pai_Lecture6_Selection%20bias.pdf](http://www.teachepi.org/documents/courses/fundamentals/Pai_Lecture6_Selection%20bias.pdf)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Sample Pop:&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Refusals, Dropouts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participants  -&gt;  Study Pop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h5&gt;Design of study&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Study setting: Where and when was the study done?  What were the circumstances?  Ethics?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Type of study: Experimental vs natural, descriptive vs analytical (trial, cohort, case-control, prevalence, ecological, case-report, etc).  If case-control or cohort, was the timing of data collection retrospective or prospective?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subjects: Who (number, age, sex, etc.)?  How were they selected?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comparison groups: What control group or standard of comparison?  How appropriate?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Study size: Was the sample size adequate to give you confidence in the finding of &quot;no association&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bias and Confounding

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a) Selection bias: Were groups comparable for subjects who entered and stayed in study?  Selection influenced by exposure (c-c) or effect (cohort) under study?  Drop-outs?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;b) Confounding: Control of potential confounding variables in design of the study - matching or subject restriction?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h5&gt;Observations&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Procedure: How are the variables in the study defined and measured, ie how were data collected?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Definition of terms: Are definitions of diagnostic criteria, measurements and outcome unambiguous?  Could be reproduced?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bias and Confounding

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a) Observation bias: Were study groups comparable for measurements or mode of observation?  Mis-classification in determining exposure or disease categories? Differential between groups, or 'random'?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;b) Confounding: Information recorded on variables that could confound the association under study (to permit adjustment in the analysis)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;THANKS Prof Sleigh!&lt;/h3&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
