<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>DisentangleThings</title>
 <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/feed/" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/"/>
 <updated>2015-09-02T11:57:20+10:00</updated>
 <id>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>ivanhanigan</name>
   <email>ivan.hanigan@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>tracking-a-data-analysis-pipeline</title>
   <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/08/tracking-a-data-analysis-pipeline/"/>
   <updated>2015-08-28T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/08/tracking-a-data-analysis-pipeline</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have just uploaded a new version of the windows build for my 'disentangle' package.  The blurb of the  draft vignette is below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be much easier to conceptually understand a complicated data
analysis pipeline than it is to implement that pipeline effectively.
This report outlines the use of the 'disentangle' R package, available from &lt;a href=&quot;http://ivanhanigan.github.io/projects.html&quot;&gt;http://ivanhanigan.github.io/projects.html&lt;/a&gt;.  This package contains functions that were developed to aid data
analysts to map out all the aspects of their work when planning and
conducting complicated data analyses using the pipeline concept.    There are often many steps in the design and analysis of a study and
when these are put together as a data analysis pipeline this addresses
the challenge of reproducibility (Peng 2006).  The
credibility of data analyses requires that every step is able to be
scrutinised (Leek 2015).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Motivating scientific questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The type of data analysis that is
the focus of this work is more complicated than simply loading some
data that are already cleaned, fitting some models and reporting some
output.  Typically the type of data analysis projects that these tools
are aimed at involve attempts to control for a large number
of inter-relationships and associations between variables. It is
especially problematic that these variables need to have been selected
by the scientists from a multitude of possible variables and a
plethora of possible data sources, during a long process of data
collection, cleaning, exploration and decision making in preparation
for data analysis. There are also a multitude of steps and decision
points in the process of model building and model checking. The use of
statistical models involving many entangled environmental and social
variables can easily result in spurious association that may be
mistakenly interpreted as causation.  Projects that the author has
been involved in include explorations of hypotheses about health effects from
droughts, bushfire smoke, heat-waves and dust-storms which produced
novel findings, and informed controversial debates about the
implications of climate change. The requirement to adequately convey
the methods and results of this research was problematic and motivated
the work on effective use of reproducible research techniques and data
analysis pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
