<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>DisentangleThings</title>
 <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/feed/" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/"/>
 <updated>2016-01-06T08:25:01+11:00</updated>
 <id>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>ivanhanigan</name>
   <email>ivan.hanigan@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Exemplars of distributing data and code - rOpenSci</title>
   <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2016/01/exemplars-of-distributing-data-and-code-ropensci/"/>
   <updated>2016-01-03T00:00:00+11:00</updated>
   <id>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2016/01/exemplars-of-distributing-data-and-code-ropensci</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The practice of distributing data and code has a wide variety of possible approaches.  There are many resources available to be used to post data and code to the internet for dissemination, and it is very easy to access these resources.  It is more difficult to find exemplars of how data and code are easily and effectively distributed.  I am conducting a review of some of the resources that describe procedures for this and present exemplars in this and following notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A paper that describes the rOpenSci project's approach is &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.5334/jors.bu&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.5334/jors.bu&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;&quot;&gt;Boettiger, C., Chamberlain, S., Hart, E., &amp;amp; Ram,
K. (2015). Building Software, Building Community: Lessons from the
rOpenSci Project. Journal of Open Research Software,
3(1). 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper is focused on the way the community development and capacity building part of the project was conducted.  The diagram shown below is introduced as an example of the style that rOpenSci recommend a data analysis workflow be constructed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/workflow-ropensci.png&quot; alt=&quot;/images/workflow-ropensci.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus on publishing data to a public repository so early in the project (prior to final analysis and manuscript) seems premature to me. But then, I do feel that I am somewhat more concerned with vexatious activity by climate skeptics than the rOpenSci team.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
