<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>DisentangleThings</title>
 <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/feed/" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/"/>
 <updated>2015-09-03T17:09:26+10:00</updated>
 <id>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>ivanhanigan</name>
   <email>ivan.hanigan@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>how-to-say-why-before-what</title>
   <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/09/how-to-say-why-before-what/"/>
   <updated>2015-09-03T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/09/how-to-say-why-before-what</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have discovered a flaw in my writing style.&lt;br/&gt;
I often say what it it before I say why it is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Example&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Disentangling health effects of environmental from social factors
is difficult for a variety of reasons. The effort to examine and
to separate environmental and social causes is nevertheless
valuable. [WHY IS IT VALUABLE?] This is especially important to
policy makers and to others who seek to maximise the public
good. A greater understanding of their respective contributions
will lead to more rational, deep-seated, lasting and effective
interventions.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The caps question is from someone reading my draft.  I need to start with the why.
Perhaps just turn the paragraph on its head?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Example&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;A greater understanding of the respective contributions from
environmental and social factors will lead to more rational,
deep-seated, lasting and effective interventions by policy makers
and to others who seek to maximise the public good.  Disentangling
health effects of environmental from social factors is difficult
for a variety of reasons. The effort to examine and to separate
environmental and social causes is nevertheless valuable.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
