<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>DisentangleThings</title>
 <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/feed/" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/"/>
 <updated>2015-10-01T12:23:48+10:00</updated>
 <id>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>ivanhanigan</name>
   <email>ivan.hanigan@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Reproducible Research Pipelines In Epidemiology</title>
   <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/10/reproducible-research-pipelines-in-epidemiology/"/>
   <updated>2015-10-01T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/10/reproducible-research-pipelines-in-epidemiology</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The scientific questions motivating my work explore the health
effects of environmental changes.  These include droughts, bushfires,
woodsmoke, dust storms, heat waves and local environmental
conditions. The research needed to disentangle health effects of
environmental changes from social factors. Some of the findings were
novel and unexpected. Adequate documentation of the methods was
problematic because of the many steps of data processing and
analysis. Reproducible research pipelines address the problem of
documenting data analyses by distributing data and code with
publications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reproducibility is needed to improve credibility.  It is often
asserted in the literature that much research is not easy to
reproduce. It is not clear what an effective way to implement these
techniques is. The thesis asks how pipelines can be effectively
implemented in epidemiology. It describes methods for reproducible
research pipelines. It also demonstrates several applications of these
methods in environmental epidemiology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Environmental epidemiology requires us to study multifactorial
pathogenesis.  All diseases have multiple causal factors. To
understand the many factors affecting health, epidemiologists must
disentangle strands of a web of causal influences. Isolating factors
is difficult and risks being overly reductionist. These determinants
can interact in complex ways. Environmental epidemiologists often
narrow the focus to a single environmental cause and health effect. A
simple example is bushfire smoke and direct effects on
cardio-respiratory disease.  A more complex example is drought and
suicide where the effects are indirect. The focus is on a chain
of intermediary causal factors. These questions are usually explored
in the context of many other factors that describe human biological
variables and the socio-economic milieu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there is greater weight given to evidence from experimental than
observational studies, experiments are difficult in environmental
health.  Analysis of observational data is often used instead. There
are problems inherent in observational studies that pertain to
variables that are confounders and effect modifiers.  Observational
studies face the principal problem of a large number of
inter-relationships between variables. These can confound or modify
effects.  It is vital to a valid analysis and meaningful
interpretation that we include these. It is problematic that
scientists select variables from a multitude of possibilities found in
the literature. Scientists also gather variables from a plethora of
possible data sources. There is a long process of hypothesising, study
design, data collection, cleaning, exploration, decision making,
preparation, data analysis, model building and model checking.  This
process has been described as a vast ‘garden of forking paths’ which
connect steps and decisions the analyst must make, but they could have
made others. These issues might result in mere
correlation interpreted as causation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adequately documenting the methods and results of data analysis helps
safeguard against such mistakes. This thesis proposes that
reproducible research pipelines address the problem of adequate
documentation of data analysis.  This is because they make it easy to
check the methods. Assumptions are easy to challenge and results
verified in new analyses. Reproducible research pipelines extend
traditional research.  They do this by encoding the steps in a
computer ‘scripting’ language and distributing the data and code with
publications.  Traditional research moves through the steps of
hypothesis and design, measured data, analytic data, computational
results (for figures, tables and numerical results), and reports (text
and formatted manuscript).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
