<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>DisentangleThings</title>
 <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/feed/" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/"/>
 <updated>2015-10-04T13:26:16+11:00</updated>
 <id>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>ivanhanigan</name>
   <email>ivan.hanigan@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Open Notebook Blogging Vs Twitter? Or Can I Do Both?</title>
   <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/10/open-notebook-blogging-vs-twitter-or-can-i-do-both/"/>
   <updated>2015-10-04T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/10/open-notebook-blogging-vs-twitter-or-can-i-do-both</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was tooling around someone's blog and noticed a link to this interesting talk &quot;Citation &amp;amp; Productivity Benefits from Open Science&quot; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/BillMills&quot;&gt;https://github.com/BillMills&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the slides markdown is here &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/BillMills/practicalOpenScience/blob/gh-pages/outline.md&quot;&gt;https://github.com/BillMills/practicalOpenScience/blob/gh-pages/outline.md&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the slide on &quot;Open Communication&quot; interested me, as I have turned up my open notebook blog to 11 recently with a couple of posts a week for the last few weeks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the recommendation to &quot;Blog Early And Blog Often&quot; resonated here!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was intrigued by the comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
used well, twitter can be a useful tool for frequent communication
paradigms as a distributor and aggregator of links to the content in
the other three bullet points. It can be really tough to stay on top
of everyone's blog, everyone's issue tracker and everything else; by
pushing links to our followers every time we have a new RFC out and
vice versa, we greatly simplify this process. See this example.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the other three being: GitHub Issues/Working Open, Blogging/Journals of Brief Ideas and
Study Preregistration/'publication bias'&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RFC means 'Request For Comments'&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and so I clicked on the link to this example &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MozillaScience/status/628990222651428864&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/MozillaScience/status/628990222651428864&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/twits.png&quot; alt=&quot;/images/twits.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Warning, Danger&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This seemed like a fascinating discussion, one that I have been thinking about a lot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and writing up here &lt;a href=&quot;https://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/09/reproducible-research-and-managing-digital-assets&quot;&gt;https://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/09/reproducible-research-and-managing-digital-assets&lt;/a&gt; in my thesis BUT...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also recently received this warning from a blogger I admire: &lt;a href=&quot;http://charliepark.org/stepping-away-from-twitter/&quot;&gt;http://charliepark.org/stepping-away-from-twitter/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He warns strongly that people with my temperament for seeking feedback and approval may be hampered by using twitter too much:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Stepping Away From Twitter
June 12, 2015
I recently noticed an interesting pattern.
On days when I’m on Twitter, my ability to focus and 
get good work done falls off a cliff.

It’s not just “when you read Twitter first-thing in the day”, 
something I’ve heard people discuss. 
It was that I was on Twitter at all.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;But there are clear benefits right?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So I had to take a step back from my recent explorations with linking up my social media and blogging interests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Looking over what I am trying to achieve by keeping regular posts of my work, along with the need I feel to make sure people who are interested can &lt;em&gt;find&lt;/em&gt; my work, I began to despair&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but then I kept digging around and see a lot of people I admire linking up twitter and more scientific communications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;So what?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I guess the real point of this post is to admit that I don't know how to use twitter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm happy to report I feel comfortable now (a couple of years in) making regular open notebook entries to communicate what is going on in my 'Lonely Analyst' lab &lt;a href=&quot;http://simplystatistics.org/2013/08/09/embarrassing-typos-reveal-the-dangers-of-the-lonely-data-analyst/&quot;&gt;http://simplystatistics.org/2013/08/09/embarrassing-typos-reveal-the-dangers-of-the-lonely-data-analyst/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but a couple of recent emails asking me for data that I published years ago &lt;a href=&quot;https://gislibrary-extreme-weather.anu.edu.au/poa_weather&quot;&gt;like this Australian Postcode Area Weather Estimates stuff&lt;/a&gt; made me think I really need to get my stuff exposed so it is &lt;strong&gt;LOT&lt;/strong&gt; more visible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
