<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>DisentangleThings</title>
 <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/feed/" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/"/>
 <updated>2014-06-15T11:27:36+10:00</updated>
 <id>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>ivanhanigan</name>
   <email>ivan.hanigan@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>reflecting-on-aekos-data-portal-test</title>
   <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2014/06/reflecting-on-aekos-data-portal-test/"/>
   <updated>2014-06-15T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2014/06/reflecting-on-aekos-data-portal-test</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/06/testing-aekos-data-portal&quot;&gt;my last post on AEKOS Dta Portal&lt;/a&gt; I reported my test of the Australian Terrestrial Ecosystem Research Network (TERN) AEKOS Data Portal system implemented by Uni Adelaide's Eco-informatics Facility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've reflected a bit on this process and I want to jot down some notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Database restore scripts are complicated and inhibit access&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'd re-iterate my conclusion that I really like how this model emphasises the use of databases for data management (and postgres or mysql are great options)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but for a less-technically savvy person or for a casual browser just looking for some quick data to play with this is not easy enough&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for a good description of alternative approaches see &lt;a href=&quot;http://flowingdata.com/2014/06/10/how-to-make-government-data-sites-better/&quot;&gt;http://flowingdata.com/2014/06/10/how-to-make-government-data-sites-better/&lt;/a&gt; which is a good set of requests for simple and efficient access to data via Government portals in the USA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I spoke with Squid and Matt the developers and they described the new enhancement they are working on now to provide a simple flat file download so that will be great.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Linking Exploratory Data Analyses back to metadata and source data documentation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In my normal mode of operating I spend more time reviewing the metadata and source data documentation before exploring data (much like the workflow described at &lt;a href=&quot;http://simplystatistics.org/2014/06/13/what-i-do-when-i-get-a-new-data-set-as-told-through-tweets/&quot;&gt;http://simplystatistics.org/2014/06/13/what-i-do-when-i-get-a-new-data-set-as-told-through-tweets/&lt;/a&gt;, especially see Step 1: Learn about the elephant)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but this time I just wanted to get some data out and so went full steam ahead like a bull at a gate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once I had &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/06/testing-aekos-data-portal/#toc_12&quot;&gt;my map visualisation done&lt;/a&gt; I decided to go back to the documentation to read up a bit more on why these locations were studied and other contextual metadata&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But when I look in the zip I downloaded I investigated the citation.pdf and the tabledefinitions.pdf but these don't really have much in it for me to link back to the source of the data and the documentation I need&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See the citation link h ref=&quot;http://www.portal.aekos.org.au/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;so hunting around the portal again I search for the survey name &quot;Department of Environment, Water and Natural Resources, South Australia - Dalhousie Survey (Scientific Expedition Group)
Survey&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and got 10 hits, chose number 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;skim-read of overview and scope. seems the link out from the overview/abstract is the most useful to get an overview&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;moved on to methods and I really like the way the segments collapse and expand as you read them, but didn't like how I had to keep navigating back and forward with the browser (like between Study Location Selection Method and Study Location Visit Method, each time I went back I had to scroll to bottom of page to get to list of sections)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally I got to explore the observation diagram and methods diagram which I have not seen before.  These seem like a great way to show the information and let people browse through the concepts etc...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But I think I still prefer an old school document with a table of contents and some kind of index.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/aekos_obs_diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;aekos_obs_diagram.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
