<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>DisentangleThings</title>
 <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/feed/" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/"/>
 <updated>2015-11-10T22:06:42+11:00</updated>
 <id>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>ivanhanigan</name>
   <email>ivan.hanigan@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Decisions to make when modelling interactions</title>
   <link href="http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/10/decisions-to-make-when-modelling-interactions/"/>
   <updated>2015-10-31T00:00:00+11:00</updated>
   <id>http://ivanhanigan.github.com/2015/10/decisions-to-make-when-modelling-interactions</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post focuses on decision making during statistical
modelling.  The case of investigating effect modification is used as
an example.  The analyst has several options available to them when
constructing the model parametrisation for adjustment to explain
modification effectively.  Unlike confounding (in which the criterion
of substantial magnitude change of the effect estimate when
controlling for a third variable can be easily assessed), models
including effect modification can be hard to interpret.  Taking
account of effect modification becomes increasingly important when
modelling complex interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an effect moderator is present then the relationship between
exposure and response varies between different levels of the
moderator. An example is provided by a paper we published, in which the
relationship between proximity to wetlands and Ross River virus
infection was found to be different for towns and rural areas, where the
'urban' variable is the 'effect moderator'.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three common ways for data analysts to address this question
in statistical models:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;multiple models for each group,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;interaction terms or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;re-parametrisation to explicitly depict interactions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first way is
to split apart the dataset and conduct separate analyses of multiple
groups. For example, one could run the regression in the urban zone
and the rural zone seperately and see if there were different exposure
response functions in the two models.  This was the approach of our paper.
This approach has the strength that it is simple to do and yeilds
results that are easy to interpret.  A limitation of this method is
that by splitting the dataset one loses degrees of freedom and
therefore statistical power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second approach (which removes that limitation of the first option) is to
fit interaction terms.  The example shown in Figure 1 is a multiplicative interaction model (Brambor 2006).
This  approach was not taken in the models reported in our paper, but can easily be implemented and shows that the function of distance was
estimated to have different 'slopes' in each of the dichotomous urban
groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statistical method can be easily implemented in
software by including a multiplicative term between two variables,
however in practice the resulting post estimation regression outputs
can be difficult to interpret.  For example, say one wants to calculate
the effect and standard error for exposure X on health outcome Y with
the interaction of the effect modifier Z.  The form of this model can
be written as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ Y ~ \beta&lt;em&gt;{1}X + \beta&lt;/em&gt;{2}Z + \beta_{3}XZ $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where B1, B2 and B3 are the regression coefficients estimated and  the term XZ is the interaction between exposure and effect modifier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difficulty for interpretation comes when using this method for calculating the marginal effect of X on Y and the conditional standard error.  The specific method described in Brambor et al. is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calculate the coefficients and the variance-covariance matrix from the regression model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The marginal effect is $\beta&lt;em&gt;{1} + \beta&lt;/em&gt;{3}XZ$ where Z is the level of the
modifying factor (0 or 1 in the dichotomous effect modifier case)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The conditional standard error is:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;$$\sqrt{var(\beta&lt;em&gt;{1}) + Z&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; var(\beta&lt;/em&gt;{3}) + 2Zcov(\beta&lt;em&gt;{1}\beta&lt;/em&gt;{3})}$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore the strengths of this approach is that it does not reduce
degrees of freedom and is straightforward to specify the model in
standard statistical software packages. The limitations are related to
interpretation of the resulting coefficients for both the main effects and the marginal effects, and standard errors for these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third approach available to analysts makes it easier to access the
resulting regression output.  This method was employed in Paper 1 in
the final modelling phase in which estimates were calculated for the
different drought exposure-response funcitons in each of the
sub-groups. In the terms of Figure \ref{fig:effectmod.png} it is simple to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calculate X1 = X * Z (i.e = exposure for condition is met, zero otherwise)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calculate X0 = X * (1-Z) (i.e. = exposure for NON-condition, zero for condition is TRUE)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instead of X, Z and XZ, fit X1, X0 and Z.  This model also contains three parameters and captures the same interactions as it is the same model with a different parametrisation.  The standard errors for the X1 and X0 are calculated directly from the regression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This method is much easier to implement and interpret.  This is also
considerably more flexible than the other two approaches.  A
limitation remains for this method in that the pre-processing steps
required are more complicated, and there are inherently more
possibilities for the data analyst to make errors in writing their
code as they make these changes to the analytical data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Demonstrating this with the data from the paper (available in table 2)
## the following code shows the different parametrisations for the effect modification by urban
## we show that the coeffs and se are equivalent but that the psuedo-R
## squared will be better when including all our data in stratified analysis

# model 0 effect in eastern
d_eastern
fit &amp;lt;- glm(cases~ buffer + offset(log(1+pops)),family='poisson', data=d_eastern )
summa &amp;lt;- summary(fit)
summa
## Coefficients:
##             Estimate Std. Error z value Pr(&amp;gt;|z|)
## (Intercept) -4.82425    0.14451 -33.382  &amp;lt; 2e-16 ***
## buffer      -0.24702    0.07921  -3.119  0.00182 **

# model 1 effect in urban
fit1 &amp;lt;- glm(cases~ buffer + offset(log(1+pops)),family='poisson', data=d_urban )
summa &amp;lt;- summary(fit1)
summa
## Coefficients:
##             Estimate Std. Error z value Pr(&amp;gt;|z|)
## (Intercept) -5.52363    0.33354 -16.561   &amp;lt;2e-16 ***
## buffer       0.03853    0.06352   0.607    0.544

# step 1, combine the urban and rural data
d_eastern$urban &amp;lt;- 0
d_urban$urban &amp;lt;- 1
dat2 &amp;lt;- rbind(d_eastern, d_urban)
str(dat2)
dat2

# model 2 is a multiplicative term
fit2 &amp;lt;- glm(cases ~ buffer * urban + offset(log(1+pops)), family = 'poisson', data = dat2)
summa &amp;lt;- summary(fit2)
summa
## Coefficients:
##              Estimate Std. Error z value Pr(&amp;gt;|z|)
## (Intercept)  -4.82425    0.14451 -33.382  &amp;lt; 2e-16 ***
## buffer       -0.24702    0.07921  -3.119  0.00182 **
## urban        -0.69938    0.36350  -1.924  0.05435 .
## buffer:urban  0.28555    0.10153   2.812  0.00492 **

# the coeff on buffer is for urban = 0 is main effect
# the coeff on buffer:urban is for urban = 1 is the marginal effect
b1 &amp;lt;- summa$coeff[2,1]
b3 &amp;lt;- summa$coeff[4,1]
b1 + b3
# 0.0385268
# but what about that p-value?  and the se?
str(fit2)
fit2_vcov &amp;lt;- vcov(fit2)
fit2_vcov
# now calculate the conditional standard error for the marginal effect of buffer for the value of the modifying variable (Z, urban =1)
varb1&amp;lt;-fit2_vcov[2,2]
varb3&amp;lt;-fit2_vcov[4,4]
covarb1b3&amp;lt;-fit2_vcov[2,4]
Z&amp;lt;-1
conditional_se &amp;lt;- sqrt(varb1+varb3*(Z^2)+2*Z*covarb1b3)
conditional_se



# model 3 is the re-parametrisation
dat2$buffer_urban &amp;lt;- dat2$buffer * dat2$urban
dat2$buffer_eastern &amp;lt;- dat2$buffer * (1-dat2$urban)

fit3 &amp;lt;- glm(cases ~ buffer_urban + buffer_eastern + urban + offset(log(1+pops)), family = 'poisson', data = dat2)
summa &amp;lt;- summary(fit3)
summa

## Coefficients:
##                Estimate Std. Error z value Pr(&amp;gt;|z|)
## (Intercept)    -4.82425    0.14451 -33.382  &amp;lt; 2e-16 ***
## buffer_urban    0.03853    0.06352   0.607  0.54416
## buffer_eastern -0.24702    0.07921  -3.119  0.00182 **
## urban          -0.69938    0.36350  -1.924  0.05435 .
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
